<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Some necessary &amp; seasonable cases of conscience about things indifferent in matters of religion, briefly, yet faithfully stated [a]nd resolved wherein the the [sic] just bounds of imposing on one hand, and of obeying on the other, are truly fixed, / by an indifferent hand.</title>
            <author>Fullwood, Francis, d. 1693.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 168 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 114 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85048</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F2517</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E2270_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209648</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868513</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868513</idno>
            <idno type="VID">160556</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A85048)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 160556)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 245:E2270[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Some necessary &amp; seasonable cases of conscience about things indifferent in matters of religion, briefly, yet faithfully stated [a]nd resolved wherein the the [sic] just bounds of imposing on one hand, and of obeying on the other, are truly fixed, / by an indifferent hand.</title>
                  <author>Fullwood, Francis, d. 1693.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24], 198 [i.e. 196], [8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed, and are to be sold at the sign of the George in Fleet-street, and the fi[r]st shop in Westminster-Hall,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>An indifferent hand = Francis Fullwood.</note>
                  <note>Page 196 misnumbered 198.</note>
                  <note>The final leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Table of contents follows text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Liberty of conscience --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:160556:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>SOME Neceſſary <hi>&amp;</hi> Seaſonable Caſes of CONSCIENCE About Things <hi>Indifferent</hi> in Matters of <hi>Religion, Briefly,</hi> yet <hi>faithfully</hi> ſtated and reſolved: wherein the the juſt <hi>bounds</hi> of <hi>Impoſing</hi> on one hand, and of <hi>Obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> on the other, are truly <hi>Fixed,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By an <hi>Indifferent</hi> Hand.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 19.</bibl>
               <p>Let us therefore follow after the things that make for <hi>peace,</hi> and things wherewith one may <hi>edifie</hi> another.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Bernard.</bibl> 
               <hi>Pacem contemnentes &amp; Gloriam quaerentes, pacem per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dunt &amp; gloriam.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed, and are to be ſold at the Sign of the <hi>George</hi> in <hi>Fleet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreet,</hi> and the firſt Shop in <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall.</hi> 1661.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:160556:2"/>
            <p>A</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:160556:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:160556:3"/>
            <head>The Preface.</head>
            <p>SAd experience in every Age, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in ours, hath taught us, that the <hi>Intereſſed Wits</hi> of men, on every ſide, having found ſo much to be ſaid for their <hi>own</hi> Opinions, and againſt <hi>anothers,</hi> have widened <hi>differences</hi> to ſo vaſt a <hi>diſtance,</hi> that the <hi>Wit of man</hi> may even deſpair of a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect <hi>cloſure.</hi> Indeed, the <hi>Wiſdome</hi> from above,
<pb facs="tcp:160556:4"/> that is pure and <hi>peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able,</hi> and the <hi>Grace</hi> of <hi>Self-denial</hi> and Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly <hi>love</hi> can onely do it.</p>
            <p>Yet, methinks, where there are <hi>two great Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies</hi> divided and enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in a Church or Kingdome, even <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral wiſdom</hi> ſhould <hi>fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee the evil,</hi> and make timely Application of <hi>preventing</hi> Remedies.</p>
            <p>For which, there ſeem but <hi>three</hi> waies open to us: <hi>Converſion</hi> or <hi>Subverſion</hi> of <hi>one</hi> of the parties, or a <hi>Conceſsion</hi> of <hi>both.</hi> The
<pb facs="tcp:160556:4"/> firſt is hardly to be <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected;</hi> the ſecond is not to be <hi>deſired;</hi> but, how happy were <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> if the laſt were <hi>obtained!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But yet I humbly crave leave to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh, betwixt <hi>that</hi> Cauſe &amp; Party which the <hi>Law</hi> owneth, and <hi>that</hi> which it doth not; neither, do I ask <hi>ſuch</hi> a <hi>Conceſsion</hi> from the preſent <hi>Law,</hi> as would maintain and uphold <hi>both</hi> theſe <hi>parties,</hi> as they are <hi>parties;</hi> one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, this I apprehend as a thing deſireable, that
<pb facs="tcp:160556:5"/> the <hi>way</hi> might be made ſo <hi>fair,</hi> or at leaſt (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the <hi>Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) paſſable,</hi> that the <hi>diſsenting</hi> party might come over to the <hi>other,</hi> and remaine no longer a <hi>diſtinct body</hi> from it. So that the <hi>perſons</hi> that uphold that which is called the <hi>illegal party,</hi> or at leaſt the <hi>main body</hi> of them (for <hi>ſome</hi> will be <hi>unreaſonable)</hi> might be <hi>preſerved,</hi> though the <hi>party</hi> be loſt; and upon a <hi>fair</hi> compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and as it were, <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding</hi> or adjoining <hi>them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the Church,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:160556:5"/> may be united and <hi>em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bodied</hi> with it, and have the <hi>ſame</hi> protection and kindeneſs of the <hi>Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If <hi>one</hi> of the <hi>parties</hi> ſhould be contented thus to <hi>ſacrifice</hi> it ſelf to the <hi>peace</hi> of the Church, and the <hi>honor</hi> of the <hi>other;</hi> it is pity, but that the <hi>ſurviving</hi> partie, that enjoyes the <hi>Inheritance,</hi> ſhould <hi>co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver</hi> the <hi>nakedneſs</hi> of its <note place="margin">Iudaicam Synagogam cum honore fuiſſe ſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liendam.</note> brother deceaſed; and, as St <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſpeaks of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church, allow him a hanſome and <hi>honorable burial.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Herein, I humbly
<pb facs="tcp:160556:6"/> conceive, conſiſts the <hi>INTEREST</hi> of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> which alſo I have made my deſigne and labour in this ſmall Treatiſe, by making the <hi>Rule of Impoſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion</hi> as low and narrow, and the <hi>Rule of Obedience</hi> as high and large as the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> the meaſure of both, would allow me.</p>
            <p>And 'tis happy that <hi>Our Intereſt</hi> is alſo <hi>our Duty;</hi> for, if, on the one ſide, nothing be <hi>required,</hi> but what is <hi>expedient</hi> in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ts due la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude; and on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb facs="tcp:160556:6"/> nothing be <hi>refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed</hi> that is not <hi>unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</hi> according to <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture,</hi> doubtleſs the <hi>way of Peace</hi> would not be ſo much unknown unto us.</p>
            <p>I do much Revere that grave ſaying of <hi>Seneca; Non expedit concutere felicem Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum;</hi> it is not ſafe to <hi>ſhake</hi> a <hi>happy</hi> State: yet, by the ſame line of <hi>rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> we are all led to uſe the beſt of our <hi>Counſels</hi> for the <hi>ſettlement</hi> of the State, and making it <hi>happy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Sentence of St
<pb facs="tcp:160556:7"/> 
               <hi>Auguſtine</hi> is alſo weighty; <hi>Ipſa mutatio Conſuetudinis, etiam quae adjuvat utilitate, novi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate perturbat,</hi> the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>change</hi> of a <hi>Cuſtom</hi> may ſometimes ſpoil any other good that may accrue by it, even by its <hi>Novelty;</hi> but, I think, none will affirm the Rule to be <hi>univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal,</hi> and to extend to <hi>all cuſtoms,</hi> and to all <hi>ſeaſons</hi> and exigents of the Church; and if that be acknowledged, what remains, but that the <hi>conveniences</hi> and <hi>inconveniences</hi> of ſome
<pb facs="tcp:160556:7"/> ſmall <hi>alterations</hi> for the <hi>gaining</hi> of <hi>ſome,</hi> yea <hi>many</hi> brethren, and the eſtabliſhment of the Church in quietneſs, be <hi>equally</hi> conſidered, and then the concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on be made and not before?</p>
            <p>I acknowledge, there is much of <hi>Wiſdome,</hi> much of <hi>Peace</hi> in that notable <hi>Adage; Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum bene poſitum non eſt movendum,</hi> an Evil that is onely ſo, becauſe <hi>inconvenient,</hi> being placed well, is not to be removed; leſt by plucking out a <hi>Ruſty</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:160556:8"/> 
               <hi>nail</hi> the whole Fabrick fall about your ears: yet its poſſible, a <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum,</hi> a little <hi>inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> ill placed may be the cauſe of a great <hi>miſchief,</hi> as the ſmalleſt errour in a curious <hi>Watch</hi> may happen to check the whole <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet, I am abſolutely averſe from that anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Petition, <hi>Tolle Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem &amp; fiet certamen,</hi> take away the Law and we will diſpute: that were, indeed, to begin <hi>in confuſion,</hi> and moſt likely to end in <hi>devour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:160556:8"/> and <hi>conſuming</hi> one another: but, I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly offer, Whether ſomething of the <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour of Law</hi> might not be abated, or ſome ſmal matters <hi>un-injoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed;</hi> not, that we might <hi>fight,</hi> but that we m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ght <hi>agree,</hi> and rejoice toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as the <hi>ſons of Peace,</hi> in <hi>Sions</hi> proſperity. I mean, not in two <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct</hi> bodies, and <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> in the Church; but, thus united, and of <hi>two made one;</hi> that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der one and the ſame <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>Law;</hi> one and the ſame <hi>Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical
<pb facs="tcp:160556:9"/> Government;</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing one and the ſame <hi>Doctrine</hi> and <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy,</hi> we might all as one man jointly proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute one and the ſame glorious <hi>ends,</hi> the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> and the ſaving of <hi>Souls.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it may not be <hi>unſeaſonable,</hi> to put the Caſe, that the <hi>Supream</hi> Authority will not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of <hi>any alteration</hi> of that which is already <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed by Law,</hi> or at leaſt not ſo much as is deſired: if it ſhould be ſo, I humbly crave leave to offer my Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice
<pb facs="tcp:160556:9"/> to my Reverend Brethren in the <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery,</hi> in a few words, and I have done.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That, as they fear the God of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and love the <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and have any bowels of compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion towards this poor people; and as they would obtain the <hi>ends</hi> of their <hi>Calling,</hi> and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance the <hi>peace</hi> and ſettlement, the <hi>ſafety</hi> and <hi>ſalvation</hi> of the Church of God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to their charge, and of which they muſt one day give an <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:160556:10"/> that they would <hi>inſtantly</hi> (ſeeing their conteſts and <hi>heats</hi> of Altercation may ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner <hi>enflame</hi> the <hi>Nation,</hi> then <hi>alter</hi> the <hi>Lawes,</hi> when once eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) that they would inſtantly throw away their envyings, hatred, malice, and variance, their evil ſurmiſings and animoſities, their evil ſpeaking and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and fall <hi>heartily</hi> to their great buſineſs the <hi>work of the Goſpel, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounding</hi> therein with <hi>love</hi> and <hi>peace</hi> one to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb facs="tcp:160556:10"/> another, and amidſt their people, that the <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Peace</hi> may be with them, and bleſs their endeavours for the <hi>common</hi> ſalvation; for why ſhould it be ſaid to their <hi>eternal obloquie,</hi> That the Church of <hi>England</hi> was <hi>deſtroyed</hi> by the <hi>Builders,</hi> or <hi>died</hi> of the <hi>Doctors?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My Dear Brethren, let me breathe out my ſoul in St <hi>Augustines</hi> words: <hi>Ut moneor, ut doleo, ut timeo; procede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem ad pedes veſtros, flerem quantum vale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem,
<pb facs="tcp:160556:11"/> rogarem quantum amarem; nunc unum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quemque pro ſeipſo, nunc utrumque pro altero; &amp; pro aliis, &amp; maximè in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmis pro quibus Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus mortuus eſt, qui vos tanquam in Theatro vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae hujus cum magno ſui periculo ſpectant; ne de vobis ea conſcribendo ſpargatis, quae quando<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> concordantes delere non poteritis, qui nunc con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordare nolitis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. To my <hi>diſſenting</hi> Brethren, my humble and <hi>ſolemn Requeſt</hi> is, that if the caſe be like to be thus, they would
<pb facs="tcp:160556:11"/> 
               <hi>in ſeaſon</hi> think it adviſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, <hi>ſeriouſly</hi> to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>what they have to do;</hi> to ſtudy that which is likely to be enjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, with <hi>all ſeverity</hi> and impartiality, as they would <hi>do</hi> or <hi>ſuffer</hi> with knowledge and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort.</p>
            <p>The great Caſe will be, <hi>Upon what grounds you may warrantably lay down your miniſtery;</hi> and, upon what, <hi>Not?</hi> or how farr you may <hi>lawfully obey</hi> the Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of Authority? For your more ample ſatisfaction herein, give
<pb facs="tcp:160556:12"/> me leave to ſay, That after the Scriptures, <hi>Bucer, Calvin, Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cthon, Zanchy, Polanus, Beza, &amp;c.</hi> are of <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted</hi> credit in <hi>ſuch a caſe</hi> as this, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be conferred with; as alſo St <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> his 118, 119. <hi>Epiſt. ad Janu.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If <hi>this</hi> poor <hi>Piece</hi> ſhall have the <hi>honour</hi> of your peruſal, I beſeech you remember, that by <hi>two Errours</hi> we are very apt to <hi>weigh</hi> things amiſs:</p>
            <p n="1">1. When we take up the <hi>ſcales</hi> &amp; weigh <hi>over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haſtily.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb facs="tcp:160556:12"/> 2. When <hi>one end</hi> of the <hi>ballance</hi> is hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vier then the other; perhaps by <hi>prejudice,</hi> or ſomething elſe that ſhould not be there.</p>
            <p>Do the <hi>Book</hi> no wrong, do the <hi>Church</hi> no wrong, do <hi>your ſelves</hi> no wrong.</p>
            <p>For your own <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation,</hi> your peoples <hi>edification,</hi> the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches peace, proſperity and <hi>ſalvation,</hi> be not averſe to any <hi>juſt ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let no <hi>Society,</hi> no <hi>Condition,</hi> no <hi>Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> with <hi>errour</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:160556:13"/> 
               <hi>ſuffering</hi> be more dear and pleaſant with you then the <hi>Church</hi> of God, the diſcharge of your <hi>truſt,</hi> the fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of your <hi>Ministery,</hi> with <hi>duty</hi> and <hi>liberty, truth</hi> and <hi>felicity.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewell.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="cases">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:160556:13"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Twenty Four Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsary and Seaſonable</hi> CASES <hi>of</hi> CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SCIENCE <hi>about things</hi> Indifferent <hi>in Matters of Religion.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="case">
               <head>CASE I. <hi>What are Things In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different?</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">Reſol.</head>
               <p>THINGS <hi>Indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent</hi> have their place in the <hi>middle,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt things <hi>Neceſſary</hi> and things <hi>Sinful;</hi> things that
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:160556:14"/> ought, and things that ought not to be done: For as to their Simple and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon <hi>Nature, i. e.</hi> Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered nakedly without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to ſuch <hi>Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> as change their proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and <hi>denominale</hi> them <hi>good</hi> or <hi>evil;</hi> they are ſuch things as may be done or left undone <hi>without ſin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They are of a Middle, not a Mixt <hi>Nature,</hi> not <hi>both</hi> good and bad; that is <note place="margin">Medium abnegati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis.</note> a <hi>Contradiction:</hi> not <hi>partly</hi> good and partly bad; then the good can never expiate the bad; (for the leaſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of evil renders the Action evil:) but neither good nor bad.</p>
               <p>As they are <hi>Morally</hi> neither good nor bad; ſo, they are not made ſuch by
<pb facs="tcp:160556:14"/> 
                  <hi>Scripture,</hi> being neither commanded nor forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den.</p>
               <p>They are of an Indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent <hi>Nature,</hi> and may be Indifferently <hi>Uſed:</hi> Yet very apt, by reaſon of Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, to <hi>tend</hi> unto, to ſwerve towards, to <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come,</hi> or <hi>appear,</hi> either good or evil.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="case">
               <head>CASE II. <hi>Whether there is any thing</hi> Indifferent <hi>in the Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of</hi> Religion?</head>
               <head type="sub">Reſol.</head>
               <p>FOR Our cleerer ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction herein, let us conſider <hi>Actions</hi> and <hi>Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:160556:15"/> 1. Touching Actions, I aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert, Firſt, That no one <hi>Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> in Religious Exerciſes is of its own nature ſo Indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent, but that by its cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances it eaſily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes good or evil.</p>
               <p n="2">2. No <hi>Action,</hi> that is <hi>deliberate,</hi> and hath an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to a certain end (di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed from Actions of <hi>fancy,</hi> uſually ſo called, which are unobſerved by the <hi>Agents) Individually</hi> conſidered, and as <hi>perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> about the Worſhip of God, can be truly Indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent; but by reaſon of its circumſtances is good or evil.</p>
               <p n="3">3. No Action, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered as a part of <hi>Divine Worſhip,</hi> can poſſibly be In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different; for either it is
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:160556:15"/> ſuch as God himſelf hath <hi>appointed,</hi> and therefore <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary;</hi> or <hi>invented</hi> by men and <hi>ſuperſtitious.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Yet Fourthly, There are divers Actions that are no <hi>part,</hi> but <hi>circumſtances</hi> of worſhip (though Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in themſelves) before they are <hi>exerted</hi> and cloth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with their circumſtances that are properly Indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, both as to their <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> neither good nor bad, as to the <hi>Scripture,</hi> neither commanded or forbidden; and conſequently: as to our <hi>uſe</hi> neither neceſſary nor unlawful: and laſtly, in <hi>compariſon</hi> with other Actions, that might as law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſerve in the ſame ſtead, of neither more or leſs neceſſity: as I might
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:160556:16"/> inſtance in lifting up, or caſting down our eyes, in lifting up or ſpreading a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad our hands in <hi>prayer, &amp;c.</hi> But thus much for Actions.</p>
               <p>2. As for <hi>Circumſtances</hi> properly ſo called, It is not doubted, I think, by any, but there are ſome, viz. <hi>time, place, habit,</hi> that are purely indifferent: I mean, befo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e they are <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined,</hi> and in a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall conſideration, abſtract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from <hi>conveniency,</hi> and not complicated with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther accidents that may vary the Caſe.</p>
               <p>I ſhall not burden this unexceptionable Point with needleſs Authority, which were very <hi>eaſie,</hi> if not needleſs. I ſhall on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:160556:16"/> inſtance the reaſonable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of it, under one part of Divine Worſhip, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Sacrament,</hi> in the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Mr. <hi>Calvin, So</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Calv. I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſti. lib 1. Sect. 43.</note> 
                  <hi>much</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>as concerns the outward form of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring the Sacrament,</hi> viz. <hi>Whether the faithful re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive into their hand, or not: Whether they divide it, or every one eat that which is given him: Whether they put the Cup into the hand of the Deacon, or deliver it to the hand of the next: Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Bread be Leavened or unleavened: Whether the Wine be red or white; it maketh no matter; theſe things be Indifferent, and left to the liberty of the Church.</hi> Thus he: and we might adde almoſt ſo many
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:160556:17"/> more of the like nature, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout every other Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, if occaſion requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="case">
               <head>CASE III. <hi>Whether may things</hi> Indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent <hi>be</hi> Impoſed <hi>and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired by Authority?</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">Reſol.</head>
               <p>DOubtleſs they may: For,</p>
               <p n="1">1. The <hi>Word</hi> of God hath not <hi>particularly</hi> taught us, what that <hi>decency</hi> and <hi>order</hi> is that is required: Yet the Ruling part of the Church ought not only to require, but to <hi>take care</hi> and ſee (according to the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles</hi>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:160556:17"/> example) that all things be done <hi>decently</hi> and in order.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Then, plain Reaſon demonſtrates, that if it be the duty of Rulers, to ſee That all things be done de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cently and in order; they muſt alſo by their own diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, or advice with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, judge and <hi>preſcribe</hi> what is ſuch.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Great <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> therefore, took upon him, not only to preſs the <hi>gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral</hi> command of decency <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 34. &amp; 11. 4. 17. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 8. 9. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 12. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 10.</note> and order; but to reprove <hi>particular</hi> diſorders, and to direct unto and command <hi>particular</hi> parts of order and comelineſſe in the Churches.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Yea, that Famous <hi>Synod,</hi> and truly Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:160556:18"/> in <hi>Acts</hi> 15. did by their power alſo limit the uſe of Indifferent things; which they concluded for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent neceſſary, Both to be <hi>ordered</hi> and to be <hi>obſerved,</hi> for the <hi>Peace</hi> of the Church.</p>
               <p n="5">5 And, that this power of <hi>ordering</hi> the Church in things <hi>indifferent,</hi> was not peculiar to the times of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> but <hi>reſides</hi> in the Rulers of the Church, to be exerted upon the ſame <hi>Moral</hi> and reaſonable oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, might eaſily be made to appear to have the ſuffrage of the <hi>Learned</hi> of all ages, if any need re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Ames</hi> himſelf having ventured to ſay, <hi>That no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ought to be command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:160556:18"/> but that which is good, or forbidden but which is</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ames, Gaſ. de Adia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phoris.</note> 
                  <hi>evil,</hi> ſeems preſently to check, and ſo to <hi>limit,</hi> as almoſt to <hi>recant</hi> what he had ſaid; adding, <hi>Quod Adiaphorum eſt, non poteſt ſimpliciter, abſolu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>è, &amp; in perpetuum, vel prohiberi vel imperari;</hi> Whereby one would think he yielded, that, for <hi>ſome reſpects,</hi> and for ſome <hi>time,</hi> things indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent in their own Nature may be commanded or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden.</p>
               <p n="7">7. I ſhall conclude this alſo with <hi>Calvins</hi> Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; <note place="margin">
                     <hi>in</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>We know,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that every</hi> Church <hi>is left free to appoint a form of</hi> po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie <hi>and government fit and profitable for it ſelf, becauſe the Lord hath preſcribed</hi>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:160556:19"/> nothing certain: to whom we might adde the perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent (if alike weighty) Teſtimony of <hi>Philip Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancton;</hi> who tels us, <hi>That becauſe the Miniſtry di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinely ordained ought to be publique and external, there is need of ſome</hi> hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane <note place="margin">In Com. Loc.</note> Ordinances.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vid etiam Danae. Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dic.</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="case">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:160556:19"/>
               <head>CASE IV. <hi>Whether may things</hi> Indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent <hi>conduce any thing to the</hi> order <hi>and decency of Gods</hi> Worſhip?</head>
               <head type="sub">Reſol.</head>
               <p>THings indifferent, <hi>ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely</hi> ſo, or conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as ſuch, cannot: For things indifferent, as ſuch, do <hi>equally reſpect</hi> the order and diſorder of the Church or ſervice thereof, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe they were not <hi>media</hi> or indifferent things, but <hi>partial.</hi> So far true is that of <hi>Ames, Thoſe things which make for order in their own Nature are not indifferent.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:160556:20"/>
               <p> However, there are <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers things</hi> in their own common nature <hi>indifferent,</hi> that yet <hi>in ſome respects</hi> are of more expediency in the Worſhip of God then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: which happens, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from their better rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſs and aptneſs for or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, as <hi>applyed;</hi> or becauſe they may have more <hi>repute</hi> or ſhew of goodneſs <hi>refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted</hi> from the <hi>temper</hi> of the <hi>place</hi> where they are uſed; and conſequently, are more <hi>eligible</hi> then thoſe that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach to <hi>vice</hi> or ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or are blemiſh'd with <hi>appearance</hi> or <hi>repute</hi> of evil, or are <hi>aliene</hi> and unapt for the <hi>preſent ſervice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again, divers <hi>Accidents</hi> that are <hi>equally</hi> indifferent in their nature, and left ſo
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:160556:20"/> by the Scripture, may alſo be equally accommodated, ſo far as we may judge, for order and decency, and conſequently both indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent and expedient; for although they all of them be decent and comely e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, yet neither the worſhippers nor the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip may be capable of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting or uſing them all, at leaſt at one and the ſame ſervice.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, the <hi>Cuſtome</hi> of the Churches is a ſtanding <hi>Rule</hi> in theſe Matters, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to which that which is <hi>decent</hi> in one Church as well as lawful in it ſelf, may be moſt <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comely,</hi> and conſequent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y moſt inexpedient in <hi>ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;</hi> which addes no little
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:160556:21"/> cleerneſs to the demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that things indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent in themſelves, may, as they are <hi>applied,</hi> conduce ſomething, yea and very much, to the order and comelineſs of Divine wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="case">
               <head>CASE V. <hi>What are thoſe things</hi> indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent <hi>that are to be deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined by the power of the Church?</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">Reſol.</head>
               <p>THeſe things indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent are apparently reducible to that <hi>General</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. <hi>ult.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Rule</hi> of the Apoſtle, <hi>Let all things be done decently</hi>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:160556:21"/> 
                  <hi>and in order:</hi> this <hi>Calvin</hi> calls <hi>that general concluſion which briefly takes in not only the whole ſtate, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven all the particular parts of outward order;</hi> Yea, ſaith he, 'tis that Rule <hi>to which all things which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect external politie are to be reduced.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>1. The ruling part of the Church hath power to ſet things IN ORDER in the Church of Chriſt: <hi>[The reſt will I ſet in order when I come.]</hi> which pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er may ſhew it ſelf in three great Inſtances. The form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a <hi>Government,</hi> of a <hi>Liturgy,</hi> and the ordering of the <hi>Manner</hi> of publick Worſhip.</p>
               <p n="1">1. I muſt (though with all reſpect and condeſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:160556:22"/> to any means of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction</hi> to the contrary) I muſt yet acknowledge, that I find ſo little of the <hi>form</hi> and frame of <hi>Church-Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> delineated in <hi>Scripture,</hi> and ſo much en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement for my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent opinion in <hi>judicious,</hi> ſober and learned Authors, that I am very apt to think that much of the <hi>Modelling</hi> of the Government of the Church is left by <hi>God</hi> to the <hi>prudence,</hi> and wiſdom, and power of the Church.</p>
               <p>I moſt readily ſubſcribe, that there is a <hi>Government</hi> of the Church, that this Government is fixed in the <hi>Officers</hi> of the Church, that the <hi>General Rules</hi> of this Government are plainly revealed in <hi>Scripture;</hi> yea,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:160556:22"/> that there was <hi>Epiſcopal Jurisdiction</hi> (in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon acceptation of it) ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercis'd by the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus,</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuch common and <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Reaſon</hi> as may bear it up, and commend its <hi>uſe</hi> to the end of the world.</p>
               <p>Yet the <hi>Frame,</hi> Faſhion, and ſpecial <hi>ſubjects</hi> of it are ſo <hi>obſcure</hi> in Scripture, and ſo little entitled to it, that, methinks, even all of all <hi>perſwaſions</hi> amongſt us are forced to <hi>prudence</hi> at laſt in the <hi>practice,</hi> though in their <hi>disputes</hi> they fetch fire from Heaven <hi>Jure Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Very many moderate <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> Divines are ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently known to content themſelves with St. <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rom's</hi>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:160556:23"/> Baſis of <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> Government, and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend it only as a <hi>prudential</hi> and <hi>occaſional</hi> (though yet <hi>Apoſtolical)</hi> Inſtitution, <hi>ad tollenda ſchiſmata,</hi> whereon I think it may ſtand as Mount <hi>Sion,</hi> and never be moved.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Presbyterians</hi> if they well conſider their <hi>ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination</hi> of <hi>claſſes</hi> they muſt needs appeal to <hi>pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> and reaſon for its de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, while they find this at leaſt as much a ſtranger to the <hi>Word</hi> of God as a <hi>ſubordination</hi> of perſons. Indeed this they <hi>of late</hi> ſeemed plainly to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, when upon the <hi>ſame</hi> grounds with their mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate brethren of the <hi>Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copal</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Conceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Deſires.</note> 
                  <hi>perſwaſion,</hi> they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceded
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:160556:23"/> to a <hi>Regulate Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy;</hi> deſiring alſo at the hands of the King that their <hi>grand grievance</hi> of too <hi>large Dioceſſes</hi> might be healed by <hi>Suffragan-Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops;</hi> which ſome think are not obſcurely anſwered already in the jurisdiction of <hi>Arch-Deacons,</hi> at leaſt, as to the aſſiſtance of the <hi>Biſhop,</hi> and the ſatisfying the deſires and complaints of our brethren aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>Yea, the very <hi>Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> it ſelf called Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents acknowledge their <hi>devolving</hi> the exerciſe of Government upon their <hi>Elders</hi> to be only for <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> ſake, and their <hi>Church-Covenant</hi> to be only neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for its ends; and at length their <hi>great Champi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">S. M.</note>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:160556:24"/> hath found no other foundation for the whole <hi>Fabrick</hi> of <hi>Congregational Diſcipline,</hi> but <hi>Mutual Confederacy</hi> and <hi>Prudential</hi> Agreement among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The <hi>ſecond</hi> thing at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed to the <hi>Care</hi> and power of the Church is the forming and eſtabliſhing of a <hi>publick Liturgy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Though we find not any ſuch form in Scripture ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther impoſed, framed or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected, yet the grounds and matter thereof are plainly there, and ſeen and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged to be there well nigh by <hi>all the Churches</hi> of Chriſt in the world.</p>
               <p>I do not find but that at the Epiſcopal Divines plead the <hi>Neceſſity,</hi> ſo moſt
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:160556:24"/> of the moderate Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians allow the <hi>lawfulneſs</hi> and the <hi>uſefulneſs,</hi> yea and the <hi>Impoſition</hi> of forms of publick Prayers, of Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtring the Sacraments, of Catechiſm, Confirmation, and of reading of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures; as alſo of repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending offenders, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> All which (as <hi>Mart. Bucer. enumerates</hi> them, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes) <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid. M. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>de reg. Chriſt. c.</hi> 13.</note> are <hi>reſerved for the care</hi> and power of the Church.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Thirdly, thereunto al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo belongs the <hi>Ordering</hi> and managing of the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Worſhip, as to the <hi>time, manner,</hi> and <hi>parts</hi> of it; when to <hi>begin,</hi> how to <hi>proceed,</hi> when to <hi>end</hi> in the <hi>ordinary</hi> courſe of Divine Service; as alſo to appoint
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:160556:25"/> 
                  <hi>extraordinary</hi> times of <hi>faſting</hi> and <hi>thanksgiving;</hi> all which, ſeeing Scripture hath left them to the <hi>Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches liberty,</hi> in reaſon they ought to be ruled and fixed by prudent <hi>Authority,</hi> as we would avoid Confuſion and Ataxie in the Church of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>2. Secondly, things ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to the <hi>Comelineſs</hi> and Beauty of Worſhip are alſo to be put to the ſame ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count; the decency of the <hi>place</hi> of Worſhip; the <hi>gravity</hi> of the <hi>habit</hi> of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters; the fitneſs of the <hi>Veſſels</hi> for both Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; the <hi>kind</hi> of bread and wine; the <hi>places</hi> and <hi>geſtures</hi> of <hi>Adminiſtration</hi> and <hi>Communion,</hi> and ſuch like, which the Scripture
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:160556:25"/> hath taken no notice of, and yet all ſober men are fully convinced that very high and almoſt indiſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble convenience exacts a ſettlement and prudent Regulation of them; and in all which, methinks, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity</hi> with <hi>Decency</hi> ſhould offend no body.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="case">
               <head>CASE VI. <hi>Whether may the</hi> Ruling <hi>part of the Church</hi> impoſe <hi>upon the Church things in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different,</hi> quatenus Indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent, <hi>or meerly becauſe they are</hi> ſuch?</head>
               <head type="sub">Reſol.</head>
               <p>I Humbly conceive they have no <hi>ſuch</hi> power, no
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:160556:26"/> ſuch <hi>Arbitrary</hi> &amp; ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly unlimited power, which, if exerciſed with any <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent,</hi> is not likely to <hi>edifie,</hi> but to deſtroy the Church.</p>
               <p>For,</p>
               <p>1. If we ſhould grant that the Governours of the Church have power to <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe</hi> things <hi>as</hi> they are <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different,</hi> or <hi>becauſe</hi> they are indifferent, we grant they have power to impoſe <hi>any thing</hi> indifferent, and conſequently <hi>what</hi> indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent things they <hi>pleaſe,</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Church: and thus we make the <hi>Will</hi> of <hi>Men</hi> the Principle and <hi>Rule</hi> of decency and order in the Service of God, and not the <hi>Will</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> or reaſon and <hi>prudence</hi> in the choice of things <hi>fitteſt</hi> according
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:160556:26"/> to his Word. Then they have power to clog <hi>Gods Worſhip</hi> with things altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>incongruous</hi> to it, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided they be indifferent in <hi>general,</hi> (as Dauncing, Bowling, <hi>&amp;c.)</hi> and to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it inſtead of a <hi>reaſonable Service,</hi> abſurd and <hi>ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous.</hi> Then may they <hi>add Ceremony</hi> upon Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, until the <hi>number</hi> is ſo many, and the <hi>weight</hi> ſo great, that the work will be <hi>burdenſome</hi> and indeed intolerable to <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Man.</hi> Thus may they im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove their <hi>Dominion over our Faith,</hi> until they have worn out the <hi>beauty of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs,</hi> the <hi>power</hi> of Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and have rendred the <hi>Chriſtian Liberty</hi> worſe <note place="margin">As <hi>Aug.</hi> complain'd</note> then the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> or <hi>Popiſh Bondage.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:160556:27"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>This Power,</hi> as God did never <hi>intruſt</hi> them with it, ſo I never heard of <hi>that</hi> man, or <hi>ſort</hi> of men, that <hi>pretended</hi> unto it, or to the exerciſe of it; every one in Authority ſtill granting that there ought to be <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> for their <hi>Impoſitions,</hi> acting therein as <hi>Men,</hi> as wel as <hi>Governors.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And though many are too apt to give <hi>Flattering Titles</hi> to men in <hi>Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> I have not met with any that Write <hi>higheſt</hi> for <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity,</hi> and obedience to Authority in things Indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent, that allowed <hi>ſuch</hi> a Power to men in Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, to require what indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent things they pleaſed, without any reſpects to the <hi>fitneſs</hi> and uſefulneſs
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:160556:27"/> of them in the <hi>Worſhip</hi> of God.</p>
               <p>For, as <hi>Thomas Rogers,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Againſt <hi>Seffray: Obi.</hi> 4.</note> (that notable Adverſary to <hi>Non-Conformity)</hi> in this Caſe ſaid, <hi>Authority in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Laws muſt alwaies re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect the Common Good. And though Church-Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernors,</hi> ſaith <hi>Francis Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Authority of the Church, &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 8 9.</note> (of the <hi>ſame spirit</hi> with the former) <hi>may make</hi> Church-Laws, <hi>yet they may not eſtabliſh what they liſt.</hi> God hath <hi>inrailed</hi> their <hi>Authority</hi> with <hi>certain bounds</hi> and limits, which they may not paſs: Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with <hi>Calvin,</hi> who hath alſo taught us, That God hath not left us <hi>effraenem li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centiam,</hi> ſuch an unbridled liberty; <hi>Sed cancellos cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundedit,</hi> in Cor. 14. ult.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="case">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:160556:28"/>
               <head>CASE VII. <hi>What then doth render things indifferent</hi> fit to be impoſed?</head>
               <head type="sub">Reſol.</head>
               <p>INDIFFERENT things though they be not commanded or forbidden <hi>particularly,</hi> but left un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decided in <hi>Scripture,</hi> yet muſt they be <hi>Reducible</hi> to, and <hi>Agreeable</hi> with ſome <hi>general Rules</hi> in <hi>Scripture,</hi> to make the Impoſition of them <hi>fit</hi> or <hi>warrantable.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Reſolution becoms <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> neither can it be <hi>inimicous</hi> to Chriſtian <hi>Diſcipline;</hi> it hath the ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frage of <hi>higheſt conformity,</hi>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:160556:28"/> which affords its liberty ſtill to challenge great conſideration in all impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions of things Indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent. <hi>Clapham,</hi> an earneſt and Learned <hi>Oppoſer</hi> of <hi>Non-Conformity,</hi> hath thus ſtated it, <hi>Such things,</hi> ſaith <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Chronol.</hi> Diſcourſe of the Church, <hi>cap.</hi> 9.</note> he, <hi>we ſay to be of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different nature; as for the doing or not doing thereof we have no</hi> expreſs <hi>Word of God in</hi> particular, <hi>only by ſome</hi> general Rule <hi>we are led to uſe our</hi> Chriſtian Reaſon. <hi>Francis Maſon</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Authority of the Church, <hi>p.</hi> 8. 9.</note> alſo allows, <hi>That all (Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical)</hi> Canons <hi>muſt be framed according to the</hi> general Canons <hi>of the holy</hi> Scripture. In a word, I never read a denial of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="case">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:160556:29"/>
               <head>CASE VIII. <hi>What are thoſe</hi> general <hi>Rules of Scripture that</hi> li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it <hi>the Impoſition of things Ind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>fferent?</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">Reſol.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>POlanus</hi> gives us a <hi>brief</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Syntag. Tom.</hi> 2. <hi>p.,</hi> 70.</note> and ſound, though a <hi>general</hi> ſatisfaction to this Caſe; <hi>Things indifferent</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ought to be redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to that general equity (which the Scriptures ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point to be the</hi> rule <hi>and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of all our actions) the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lex reſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit ordine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ad bonum commune.</hi> Aquinas.</note> good of our Neighbour. <hi>Quatenus ad Dei Gloriam, &amp; proximi ſalutem faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt:</hi>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:160556:29"/> or the <hi>Common good,</hi> as <hi>Rogers</hi> ſhortens it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Marlorate</hi> doth more <note place="margin">In 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. <hi>ult.</hi>
                  </note> fully explicate himſelf, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth his <hi>Traditions</hi> by <hi>the Word of God,</hi> Reaſon, Edification, <hi>the</hi> Example <hi>of Churches,</hi> Decency <hi>and Order;</hi> and he adds, <hi>With which ſame</hi> Arguments <hi>we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ght to examine our</hi> Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Traditions.</p>
               <p>But let us a little conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſome more <hi>ſpecial</hi> Rules, as we eaſily find them in the <hi>ſurface</hi> of the <hi>Scripture.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. The firſt ſhall be that <hi>Catholique</hi> Rule of <hi>Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diency.</hi> All things, (ſaith <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 12</note> the <hi>Apoſtle) are</hi> Lawfull <hi>for me; but all things are not</hi> expedient. Some <hi>law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful</hi>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:160556:30"/> things, it ſeems, are not <hi>expedient.</hi> Things not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient to be <hi>done,</hi> ought not to be <hi>done;</hi> and things not expedient to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, ought not to be commanded.</p>
               <p>Thus there falls before us a <hi>double lawfulneſs;</hi> a thing may be <hi>lawful</hi> and <hi>expedient;</hi> a thing may be <hi>lawful,</hi> and not <hi>expedient;</hi> or a thing may be lawful, and yet we ought <hi>not</hi> to do it, becauſe <hi>not expedient;</hi> and a thing may be lawful, and we ought to do it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe expedient: And thus a thing may be lawful and not lawful.</p>
               <p>More plainly, there is a <hi>lawfulneſs</hi> more remote from us, which is fixed in the <hi>general</hi> nature of the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:160556:30"/> thing; this is meant in the firſt expreſſion of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>All things are lawful</hi> for me. 2. There is a <hi>law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs</hi> that is more <hi>imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate</hi> and nearer to us, which dependeth <hi>not</hi> upon the <hi>common</hi> eſſence of the thing, but upon ſome <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinſick</hi> circumſtances, of <hi>Time, Place, Occaſion,</hi> &amp;c. whereby the thing is <hi>fitted</hi> to the <hi>preſent</hi> ſervice; this the Apoſtle means by <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediency, All things are not expedient.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now where you ſpeak of this <hi>latter</hi> lawfulneſs of <hi>expediency,</hi> the former, <hi>viz.</hi> of <hi>Indifferency</hi> is ſhut out: ſo that though in one ſence, all things that are <hi>indifferent</hi> are <hi>lawful,</hi> yet in this latter ſence, all
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:160556:31"/> things that are indifferent and <hi>not expedient,</hi> are <hi>not lawful,</hi> but ſinful: And it being againſt the <hi>Rule</hi> of the Apoſte, and indeed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt common <hi>reaſon;</hi> it is not warrantable for Church-Governors to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe any thing about Gods Worſhip, that is <hi>only</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different and lawful in it ſelf, but <hi>not expedient.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus that great Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of our Church and the Ceremonies of it extends and limits her power; <hi>Church-Governors</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>have liberty to eſtabliſh whatſoever being in it ſelf</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Authority of the Church, <hi>p.</hi> 13.</note> 
                  <hi>indifferent ſhall to their Wiſedom</hi> ſeem moſt expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The <hi>ſecond</hi> ſpecial Ru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e is the <hi>publique Peace.</hi>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:160556:31"/> God is <hi>the God of Peace and Order;</hi> of Peace as well as Order; and as the <hi>Order,</hi> ſo the <hi>Peace</hi> of the Church, without which there is <hi>no</hi> Order, is preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous with him, and with all that have the <hi>Spirit</hi> of God, and any care of his Church.</p>
               <p>Should any thing give way to <hi>Peace,</hi> and ſhould not things <hi>Indifferent?</hi> are not theſe <hi>Indifferent?</hi> is not Peace <hi>neceſſary?</hi> is it not neceſſary by <hi>command?</hi> Yea, it is neceſſary as a <hi>means;</hi> as a means of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting our <hi>fears,</hi> of <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining</hi> our <hi>hopes,</hi> our hopes of ſettlement, our hopes of unity, our hopes of plenty, of proſperity and glory in Church and State.</p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:160556:32"/>
               <p> Who can think it <hi>wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> (without ſome other greater <hi>inconvenience</hi> urge to it) to <hi>force</hi> any thing that is <hi>but indifferent,</hi> to the endangering ſo neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary a thing as <hi>Peace,</hi> or the <hi>dividing</hi> the Church of God, or <hi>provoking</hi> any conſiderable part thereof to <hi>ſeparate</hi> from us? Let us rather with the <hi>Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Synod,</hi> weigh the <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent neceſſity</hi> in this regard; and as the Apoſtle exhorts in the like caſe, <hi>Follow the things that make for Peace,</hi> Rom. 14. 19.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The <hi>third</hi> ſpecial Rule in <hi>Scripture</hi> is, the <hi>of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of weak brethren,</hi> who though weak are not to be thrown to the walls without any regard.</p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:160556:32"/>
               <p> Yea, the <hi>Scripture</hi> rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons <note place="margin">Vid. Rom. 14. 1 Cor. 7, 9, 10. <hi>cap.</hi>
                  </note> us to a <hi>greater tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> to the <hi>weaker part</hi> of the Church; and more <hi>care</hi> of that: and in this very caſe hath given us di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers and weighty Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations, that we wilfully <hi>offend</hi> not our weak Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren by the uſe of our <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty</hi> in things <hi>indifferent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Indeed, when things indifferent are once com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, the caſe is alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, as to <hi>private</hi> Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, (as at large hereafter) but otherwiſe, where the <hi>reaſon</hi> of the Apoſtle's <hi>Example</hi> and <hi>Commands</hi> is found, the <hi>obligation</hi> of both will hardly be eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped.</p>
               <p>As <hi>Polanus</hi> ſaith, That <note place="margin">Syntag. tom. 2. p 376.</note> 
                  <hi>Ceremonies may be obſerved</hi>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:160556:33"/> 
                  <hi>for peace ſake, and the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voiding of the offence of the weak:</hi> ſo, I humbly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, that the <hi>rigor</hi> of <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition</hi> may be warranta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly abated for the ſame cauſes.</p>
               <p>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Rogers</hi> is more pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remptory <note place="margin">Againſt <hi>Seffray.</hi> Object. 4.</note> (though, as I no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted before, a ſufficient De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender of <hi>Ceremonies)</hi> He that in <hi>things indifferent</hi> (meaning, before they are commanded) hath not a <hi>tender</hi> care of <hi>weak Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians</hi> in his doing, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that there is not that <hi>charity</hi> in him, nor regard of his brethren which God requireth.</p>
               <p>Upon this ground, no doubt, the Learned Doctor <hi>Gardner</hi> ſtood, when he ſaid, <hi>If the Laws in theſe</hi>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:160556:33"/> 
                  <hi>caſes,</hi> viz. <hi>of Ceremonies, had not been already made, I ſhould never for my own part wiſh to have them made.</hi> Dialogue about Ceremonies.</p>
               <p>Neither, can we referr to any other <hi>Topick</hi> the care and pains that Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> and King <hi>James</hi> uſed for the juſt ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Non-conformiſts</hi> in the ages before us: To the <note place="margin">1 Cor. 9. 22, 13.</note> 
                  <hi>weak,</hi> became I as <hi>weak,</hi> that I might <hi>gain</hi> the <hi>weak—</hi>and this I do (ſaith the <hi>great Apoſtle)</hi> for the <hi>Goſpels</hi> ſake.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The <hi>fourth</hi> ſpecial Rule may be Edification, the grand <hi>Level</hi> of <hi>all</hi> Church power: the <hi>Edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi> of the Church, and not its <hi>deſtruction</hi> in the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:160556:34"/> 
                  <hi>whole,</hi> or (if poſſible to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void it) in <hi>any part.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore, the great <note place="margin">Rom. 14. 15. <hi>In quo Charitas moderatrix eſt,</hi> Calv. Rom. 14. 10.</note> principle of all ſuch impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions muſt be <hi>charity</hi> and love to our Brethren; not <hi>envy</hi> at, or deſire of <hi>revenge</hi> upon <hi>any perſon</hi> or <hi>party</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe minded: not to ſhew victory over them, or <hi>dominion over their faith</hi> or <hi>actions;</hi> things, I doubt not, ſincerely abhorred by our <hi>preſent</hi> Governours as well as by our <hi>former;</hi> but <hi>forbearing one another in love,</hi> and forgiving one another, as Chriſt alſo hath given us example, ſhewing all bowels and tenderneſs <hi>in all waies</hi> and means of an <hi>happy</hi> accord and <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. Fiftly, the moſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:160556:34"/> Rule of all is that of the Apoſtle, <hi>Let all things be done decently and in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der:</hi> a ſtanding Rule never to be croſſed by any Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority under heaven; yea, the <hi>God of heaven,</hi> being the God of <hi>Order,</hi> will never reverſe it. Then nothing that is either <hi>inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent</hi> or diſorderly in Gods Worſhip can warrantably be impoſed upon his Church. The <hi>contrary</hi> whereof, I think, had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver hitherto the honour to be aſſerted.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Clapham,</hi> ſpeaking of things indifferent, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Chron. c.</hi> 9.</note> which (ſaith he) the Apoſtle ſheweth, that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency and order muſt be obſerved; but <hi>for parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars,</hi> he hath no particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:160556:35"/> 
                  <hi>injunction</hi> from the <hi>Lord.</hi> Chron. <hi>cap.</hi> 9.</p>
               <p>Provided alwaies, ſaith M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Maſon,</hi> that all things <note place="margin">pag. 13.</note> be done <hi>honeſtly and in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. The ſixth Rule is <hi>Cuſtome:</hi> of very great uſe to indicate what is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent and orderly; ſeeing by the force of <hi>Cuſtome,</hi> that is comely in <hi>one</hi> Country, that is plainly ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd in <hi>another.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cuſtome</hi> is the <hi>Umpire</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11. 26.</note> 
                  <hi>in indifferent</hi> things: <hi>If any man ſeem to be conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>we have no ſuch Cuſtome.</hi> No doubt, 'tis <hi>dangerous</hi> to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduce <hi>innovations,</hi> and by <hi>new</hi> impoſitions to force againſt the <hi>Uſages</hi> and Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes of the place where
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:160556:35"/> we live: 'Tis well known, how much weight <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe, Auguſtine,</hi> and the reſt of the Fathers laid upon this both for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and their <hi>advice</hi> to others.</p>
               <p>We <hi>have</hi> no ſuch Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, <hi>nor the Churches of God.</hi> Doubtleſs, the more <hi>extenſive</hi> a Uſage is, the more <hi>ancient,</hi> the more <hi>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſal,</hi> the <hi>longer</hi> and <hi>farther</hi> a thing hath been practiſed in the Churches of God, the more it ought to be <hi>regarded,</hi> both by the governing and governed parts of the Church, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Rule of the Fathers.</p>
               <p n="7">7. The <hi>laſt</hi> Rule is <hi>Gospel liberty:</hi> this muſt not be <hi>invaded</hi> by any im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:160556:36"/> though it muſt not be <hi>miſtaken.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gospel</hi> liberry can hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be infringed if <hi>theſe Rules</hi> be heeded in the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of things indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That <hi>nothing</hi> indifferent be impoſed that any way checketh with the former Rules of <hi>expediency, peace, offence</hi> of the weak, <hi>edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, decency, order,</hi> and the <hi>cuſtome</hi> of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That things <hi>indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent</hi> be not impoſed as if they were <hi>in themſelves neceſſary;</hi> which Divines aſſert to be <hi>Superſtition.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. That things indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent be not required with <hi>equal ſeverity</hi> as things ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:160556:36"/> 4. That ſuch things when impoſed be <hi>declared</hi> by the Impoſers to be <hi>mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table</hi> in their nature, and to be altered upon <hi>juſt</hi> oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion.</p>
               <p n="5">5. That things indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent be not impoſed in ſo great a <hi>number</hi> as is really <hi>burthenſome</hi> to the Church of God; which was much in the care of our firſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Concerning the <hi>multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude</hi> of Ceremonies of idle and vain nature (ſaith Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop <note place="margin">In Apol.</note> 
                     <hi>Jewel)</hi> we know that S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                     <hi>Auguſtine</hi> did much complain of them in his time; and therefore we have greatly <hi>diminiſhed</hi> the <hi>number</hi> of them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we know, that they were <hi>troubleſome</hi> to
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:160556:37"/> good conſciences and <hi>burthenſome</hi> to the Church: yet we retaine and have likeing, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of <hi>thoſe</hi> Ceremonies which we are ſure were <hi>delivered</hi> us from the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles;</hi> but ſome <hi>others</hi> too beſides, which we thought might be ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red without <hi>hurt</hi> to the Church of God: becauſe we affected that all things in the <hi>Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> might (according to the will of the Apoſtle) be done with <hi>comlineſs</hi> and good <hi>order.</hi> But all ſuch things which we perceived to lean to <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition,</hi> or to be of no uſe, or bald, or toyiſh, or againſt the ſacred <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures,</hi> or elſe <hi>unmeet</hi> for
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:160556:37"/> ſober and wiſe people, whereof there is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed <hi>Chaos</hi> in the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Synagogue,</hi> all theſe we have utterly renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced and caſt off, becauſe we would not have the Worſhip of God <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded</hi> and combred with ſuch <hi>follies.</hi>
                  </q> Thus that moſt excellent Man. The ſumm of whoſe words here recited, doth in effect contain and confirm all that I have ſaid upon this Caſe; <hi>viz.</hi> That the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies of the Church ought to be <hi>expedient, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent</hi> and orderly, not <hi>hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</hi> to the Church, not <hi>troubleſome</hi> to good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, not <hi>burdenſome:</hi> And he adds, that <hi>our own</hi> Church in the <hi>firſt</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:160556:38"/> had regard to the ſaid <hi>Rules.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let me conclude with an humble Petition, that I be not <hi>mis-interpreted</hi> to <hi>preſcribe</hi> to <hi>Authority</hi> in what I have ſaid: I have onely <hi>marked</hi> the <hi>general</hi> Rules in Scripture, leaving <hi>particulars</hi> to the liberty and <hi>wiſedom</hi> of Superiors; to whom I only take bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to offer, that they ought to walk by <hi>theſe Rules,</hi> &amp; ſettle the Church and Worſhip of God in <hi>peace</hi> and <hi>order,</hi> with all comlineſs and expediency.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="case">
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:160556:38"/>
               <head>CASE IX. <hi>How are</hi> private <hi>perſons to demean themſelves un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſuch</hi> impoſitions <hi>of Authority in</hi> religious <hi>Exerciſes?</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">Reſol.</head>
               <p>VVE have hitherto, rather, labored to diſcover the <hi>reaſon of Impoſing,</hi> and the due <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent</hi> of Eccleſiaſtical Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority in things <hi>indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent;</hi> endeavouring alſo to draw <hi>that</hi> as <hi>narrow</hi> and ſtraight, and as much to <hi>Rule</hi> as may be; yet, I hope, without <hi>juſt</hi> offence to the ſame.</p>
               <p>We are now deſcending to take a <hi>view</hi> of the <hi>rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:160556:39"/> of obedience;</hi> and to conſider the <hi>extent</hi> of their <hi>duty,</hi> who are under <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand.</hi> Where, that I may appear <hi>impartial</hi> and for <hi>peace indeed,</hi> I muſt be <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonant</hi> to my Deſigne, and labour to dis-intangle and <hi>enlarge</hi> the <hi>conſciences</hi> of <hi>private</hi> perſons, with as much freedom towards <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity</hi> as lawfully I may; that, having brought the <hi>Injunction</hi> as <hi>low</hi> and nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and the <hi>Obedience</hi> as <hi>high</hi> and large as we may, the <hi>commanders</hi> and the <hi>commanded</hi> may be happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly found <hi>nearer</hi> together, and in ſweeter communion one with another.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Charity,</hi> ſurely, will not be diſpleaſed at this harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs project, but will be
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:160556:39"/> ready with a <hi>pardon,</hi> though I fail of <hi>ſucceſs,</hi> or too <hi>imprudently</hi> manage the Attempt; eſpecially, while my <hi>Aime</hi> is levelled at ſo <hi>deſireable</hi> an <hi>end,</hi> the <hi>peace</hi> of the Church &amp; the <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon good;</hi> and uſe no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Engine</hi> to draw <hi>down</hi> the <hi>one,</hi> and <hi>raiſe</hi> the <hi>other,</hi> but <hi>that</hi> from heaven, the <hi>holy Scripture.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And to the <hi>Caſe</hi> in <hi>gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral,</hi> which is this [How are <hi>private</hi> perſons to demean themſelves under the commands of Authority or Eccleſiaſtical <hi>Laws,</hi> in <hi>Religious</hi> Exerciſes?] I ſhall now (the Lord aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing me) betake my ſelf, with <hi>all conſcience</hi> and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity, to anſwer, breaking it into ſeveral <hi>particular</hi>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:160556:40"/> 
                  <hi>caſes,</hi> according as the <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject</hi> of <hi>humane Injunctions</hi> may be <hi>diſtinguiſhed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Object of humane Injunction,</hi> or that which is injoyned or commanded, may be proceeded upon, by a <hi>gradation</hi> or deſcent of <hi>five ſtepps:</hi> for that which is injoyned, is either <hi>neceſſary, expedient, purely indifferent, inexpedient,</hi> or <hi>unlawfull.</hi> Accordingly, there may be offered <hi>five Caſes,</hi> viz. what a <hi>private</hi> perſon ought to do, when things <hi>neceſſary,</hi> or things <hi>expedient,</hi> or things <hi>purely indifferent,</hi> or things <hi>inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient,</hi> or things <hi>unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</hi> are required by Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority in the exerciſes of <hi>Religion:</hi> to <hi>all</hi> which we addreſſe our
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:160556:40"/> ſelves to apply a ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and <hi>particular ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="case">
               <head>CASE X. <hi>What ought a</hi> private <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian to do, when things</hi> neceſſary <hi>in themſelves are</hi> required <hi>by Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity?</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">Reſol.</head>
               <p>BOth for the <hi>Intention</hi> of the preſent <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe</hi> (we treating proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly about things indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent) as alſo, for the very <hi>nature</hi> of the <hi>thing</hi> it ſelf, this need not be put to the <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For though ſome have
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:160556:41"/> thought they have ſeen reaſon enough, not ſo farr to countenance an <hi>Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation,</hi> as to do their <hi>duties</hi> when commanded there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto by <hi>unlawfull</hi> powers; from the liberty of that trite Rule, <hi>Affirmative Precepts do not binde to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very particular inſtance of time:</hi> yet, it were a <hi>ſtrange</hi> perverſneſs in any, not to do that which God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires, becauſe his <hi>Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerent,</hi> lawfull Authority requires it alſo, even in the things of <hi>Gods Worſhip.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Optatus</hi> reckoned it a <hi>madneſs</hi> in <hi>Donatus,</hi> that broke forth in that queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his, <hi>Quid Imperatori cum Eccleſia, What hath the</hi> KING <hi>to do with the</hi> Church? But <hi>Optatus</hi> wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:160556:41"/> anſwered, <hi>The Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth is not in the Church, but the Church is in the Commonwealth;</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently, <hi>he</hi> that is Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor of the <hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth</hi> is ſo of the Church; and the Rule is, <hi>The Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel takes</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Non tollit praecepta naturae &amp; legis, ſed perficit,</hi> Rom. 3. ult.</note> 
                  <hi>not away the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of</hi> Nature, <hi>and the</hi> Moral <hi>Law, but eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and perfects them, and rather enlargeth and</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms, <hi>then any way</hi> weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens Obedience <hi>to Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore are we to <hi>pray</hi> for <hi>Kings,</hi> that under their <hi>pious</hi> and religious gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, we may not live in <hi>peace,</hi> and <hi>honeſtly</hi> only, but in <hi>godlineſs, in all godlineſs,</hi> as the Apoſtle directs us:</p>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:160556:42"/>
               <p> St <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> upon thoſe <note place="margin">Contra <hi>Creſcon.</hi> lib. 3. cap. 51.</note> words in the ſecond <hi>Pſalm</hi> ſaith, <hi>Kings</hi> (not onely as <hi>men,</hi> but as they are <hi>Kings) ſerve the Lord,</hi> if in their Kingdomes they <hi>command</hi> that w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> is <hi>good,</hi> and prohibite that which is <hi>evil;</hi> not only in thoſe things which appertain to <hi>humane</hi> Society, <hi>verùm e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam in iis quae ad divinam Religionem,</hi> but alſo in matters concerning Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and divine Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Who</hi> dare offer to name the <hi>Time</hi> ſince the <hi>World began</hi> (the <hi>Times of perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution</hi> which rendred it im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible only excepted) wherein <hi>God</hi> did not <hi>allow,</hi> &amp; Governours both <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral</hi> and <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> did
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:160556:42"/> not <hi>aſſume</hi> the power of governing &amp; giving <hi>Lawes</hi> to the <hi>Church,</hi> for the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of their duties in <hi>matters of Religion?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As ſoon as the black and <hi>bloody cloud</hi> was diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell'd, by the <hi>favour</hi> and power of glorious <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine,</hi> he aſſumed this <hi>Supremacy;</hi> he put down <hi>Idolatry,</hi> he eſtabliſh'd the <hi>Truth;</hi> he compoſed <hi>dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences</hi> among <hi>Biſhops,</hi> ſuppreſſed <hi>Hereſie</hi> and <hi>Schiſm,</hi> called <hi>Councils,</hi> and gave his <hi>ſuffrage</hi> in them; he heard and judged <hi>Cauſes</hi> in <hi>Religion,</hi> and made <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Laws</hi> and Edicts; and all this, (as <hi>Euſebius</hi> ſaith) <hi>tanquam communis Epiſcopus à Deo</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Euſeb.</hi> de vita <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtan.</hi> lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. cap. 37.</note> 
                  <hi>conſtitutus,</hi> as a common
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:160556:43"/> Overſeer or Biſhop <hi>ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned</hi> of God; and I may adde, as an excellent <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample</hi> to all <hi>Chriſtian Princes</hi> to the end of the world.</p>
               <p>Doubtleſs, if he that <hi>reſiſts</hi> a <hi>lawfull</hi> power ſhall <hi>receive</hi> to himſelf <hi>damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> he ſhall hardly eſcape that <hi>reſiſts</hi> his command in <hi>lawfull,</hi> yea, in <hi>neceſſary</hi> things; wherein (if in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing) he ought to obey, for the <hi>Lords ſake,</hi> and to ſubmit in <hi>conſcience</hi> of his duty to <hi>God</hi> as well as <hi>Man;</hi> for, as <hi>Auguſtine, Hoc jubent Imperatores, quod jubet &amp; Chriſtus; quia cum bonum jubent, per illos non Chriſtus niſi jubet:</hi> ſo that when <hi>Kings</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, what <hi>Chriſt</hi> has <hi>firſt</hi>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:160556:43"/> commanded, <hi>Chriſt</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands <hi>by them,</hi> and we are called to obey not onely <hi>them</hi> but <hi>Chriſt</hi> in them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="case">
               <head>CASE XI. <hi>What</hi> private <hi>perſons are to do, when</hi> things expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent <hi>are required of them?</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">Reſol.</head>
               <p>THE <hi>ſecond</hi> ſort of things enjoyned in the exerciſe of <hi>Religion,</hi> we have propoſed to be things <hi>expedient</hi> for their <hi>preſent</hi> and <hi>special</hi> uſe, though not <hi>neceſſary</hi> in their <hi>common</hi> nature, or <hi>particularly</hi> comanded by
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:160556:44"/> 
                  <hi>God.</hi> And the Queſtion is, <hi>When ſuch things are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired by lawfull Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, whether private perſons are bound in duty to obey or not?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Some perſons, I believe, like not, that any <hi>ſuch</hi> thing ſhould be <hi>impoſed</hi> u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon them; but would ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have the <hi>Decent orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi> of <hi>Gods</hi> Worſhip left to their own <hi>private</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion: yet I hope better of my Brethren, then that they ſhould refuſe the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of any thing which <hi>themſelves</hi> allow, becauſe it is alſo approved by <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> and commanded by <hi>Authority;</hi> and therefore, to be <hi>diſorderly</hi> in the Church of God, becauſe they are <hi>enjoyned</hi> to do things in <hi>order:</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:160556:44"/>
               <p> Such things as we know to be fitted for the <hi>decency</hi> and order of <hi>Gods Worſhip</hi> if enjoyned by a lawfull Authority, though they be not <hi>neceſſary</hi> in their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon <hi>nature,</hi> or <hi>particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> commanded by God; and thus, though they want a <hi>primary</hi> neceſſity; yet they ſeem, in the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all ſober men; to contract a treble <hi>ſecunda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> neceſſity, to <hi>oblige</hi> us to obedience; <hi>viz.</hi> from the <hi>general commands</hi> of <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture,</hi> from the <hi>particular injunction</hi> of <hi>Authority;</hi> and the urging <hi>direction</hi> of our own <hi>conſcience;</hi> where <hi>God,</hi> indeed, ſeems to ſpeak <hi>thrice</hi> at once unto us; by the <hi>Rule</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> the <hi>Law</hi> of the <hi>Land,</hi> and
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:160556:45"/> the <hi>voice</hi> of our own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed <hi>Conſciences.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Such <hi>Conſtitutions</hi> (ſaith <hi>Bullinger)</hi> as are <hi>expedient</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Dec. 2. Sect. 1.</note> and drawn from <hi>general Scripture,</hi> and are for <hi>edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication,</hi> I call not <hi>Humane Traditions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yea, one of the <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med</hi> Churches have put it <note place="margin">Confeſ. Suev. in Harm. Confeſ. 8. 17. pag. 290.</note> into their very <hi>Confeſſion,</hi> That they deſerve to be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed <hi>Divine</hi> rather then <hi>Humane Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For, ſaith M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Calvin,</hi> ſuch are not to be reckoned for <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Calv.</hi> in 1 Cor. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>humane Traditions,</hi> ſince they are founded in the <hi>ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral precept,</hi> and have the <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Zanch.</hi> in com. loc. 16.</note> liquid approbation, as it were, of <hi>Chriſts own mouth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Beza,</hi> therefore, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Beza</hi> Epiſt. 24.</note>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:160556:45"/> That things that make <hi>for order,</hi> being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by Authority, do ſo far binde the <hi>conſcience,</hi> that no man can <hi>wilfully</hi> tranſgreſs them <hi>without ſin.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="case">
               <head>CASE XII. <hi>What are</hi> private <hi>perſons to do, when things that are</hi> purely Indifferent <hi>are required in Religious Exerciſes?</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">Reſol.</head>
               <p>THat thing I here call <hi>purely Indifferent,</hi> w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> impartially retaines a <hi>midd</hi> place betwixt things <hi>neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary</hi> and things <hi>ſinfull,</hi> and
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:160556:46"/> betwixt things <hi>inexpedient</hi> and things <hi>expedient;</hi> more plainly, we take a thing to be <hi>purely indifferent,</hi> here, that is neither <hi>neceſſary</hi> or <hi>ſinfull</hi> in its <hi>nature,</hi> or by the <hi>Word</hi> of God; nor yet <hi>expedient</hi> or <hi>inexpedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent,</hi> as to the <hi>uſe</hi> for which it is appointed, but in <hi>all</hi> regards <hi>purely Indifferent,</hi> being neither neceſſary with a primary or with a ſecundary neceſſity, as we lately diſtinguiſhed; nor yet reſpectively ſinfull or unlawfull, <hi>viz.</hi> either with a primary or ſecundary ſinfulneſs.</p>
               <p>Now the Queſtion is <hi>not</hi> whether there be any <hi>ſuch things,</hi> or not; but, <hi>hoc ſuppoſito,</hi> ſuppoſing there are, and that they are
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:160556:46"/> 
                  <hi>commanded</hi> by lawfull Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority; the Queſtion is, <hi>What private Chriſtians are to do in ſuch a caſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For my part, though (as I have ſaid) <hi>ſuch</hi> things <hi>ought not</hi> to be enjoyned by Authority; yet, if the <hi>Scales</hi> be <hi>even</hi> before, the <hi>command</hi> of Authority muſt (I think) of neceſſity <hi>turn</hi> them.</p>
               <p>So that here we muſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve a <hi>third</hi> kinde of <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity,</hi> where the two <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi> are wanting: ſo that, where a thing is not <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary properly,</hi> or <hi>occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionally,</hi> as <hi>expedient,</hi> yet, it may <hi>become</hi> neceſſary by the addition of a <hi>hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Law;</hi> which alſo <hi>circulates</hi> into the <hi>firſt</hi> neceſſity of a <hi>divine</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand;
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:160556:47"/> 
                  <hi>Submit your ſelves to every Ordinance of man for the Lords ſake:</hi> though it be but a meer humane Ordinance, yet, (as ſuch) if not <hi>ſinfull</hi> or forbidden by God, you ſeem com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to ſubmit unto it.</p>
               <p>Conſequently, we have diſcovered a <hi>third</hi> kinde of <hi>ſinfulneſs,</hi> where the <hi>primary</hi> and <hi>ſecundary</hi> is wanting: ſo that, where a thing is not ſinfull <hi>in it ſelf,</hi> or by any <hi>inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> in its uſe, yet it may become ſo, by <hi>diſobedience</hi> to lawfull Authority: <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey them that have the Rule over you, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit your ſelves:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis neceſſary we obſerve a difference in the <hi>reaſon of</hi>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:160556:47"/> 
                  <hi>impoſing</hi> and of <hi>obeying;</hi> For, before a thing is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, there is no <hi>obligation</hi> upon Authority to require it, if it be not fit; yea, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there is a <hi>pre-obligation</hi> to impoſe nothing but what is <hi>expedient</hi> in the Worſhip of God; but now, when a thing is <hi>once required,</hi> though not <hi>expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient,</hi> as we could deſire, we are under in <hi>obligation;</hi> and we muſt not conſult our liberty but our <hi>duty:</hi> or if our <hi>liberty,</hi> not ſo much our <hi>liberty to forbear,</hi> as our <hi>liberty to obey;</hi> and to enquire whether the thing be <hi>lawful</hi> or not, whether <hi>God</hi> wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>allow</hi> us to do it or not; and if <hi>ſo,</hi> Whether it be not our du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and whether, though
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:160556:48"/> we would not do it for the <hi>things ſake,</hi> we muſt not do it for the <hi>commands ſake;</hi> the command of <hi>Man,</hi> and the command of <hi>God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wherefore <hi>Beza</hi> (to whom I might add the <hi>Learned</hi> of moſt <hi>ranks</hi> and ages, if need required) is ſo expreſs, <hi>Res Alioqui per ſe medioe, &amp;c.</hi> 
                  <q>Things of middle and indifferent na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture do after a <hi>certain man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner change</hi> their <hi>nature,</hi> when by lawful Authority they are either <hi>comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded</hi> or <hi>forbidden,</hi> becauſe it is not lawful to <hi>omit</hi> againſt the <hi>Precept</hi> when it is commanded, or to act againſt the <hi>prohibiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> when it is forbidden.</q> Thus <hi>Beza:</hi> an <hi>undoubted</hi>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:160556:48"/> Teſtimony in the <hi>Caſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But we need <hi>no more,</hi> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the thing hath been <hi>granted long agon</hi> by a <hi>nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous body</hi> of <hi>Non-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply to Mr. <hi>Powel, p.</hi> 2l</note> 
                  <q>
                     <hi>In things</hi> (ſay they) <hi>truly indifferent,</hi> it is <hi>always</hi> juſtified, and ſhall be <hi>farther juſtified</hi> if need require, that we attribute <hi>no leſs</hi> to the <hi>Magiſtrates,</hi> then o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r <hi>Adverſaries</hi> (meaning the <hi>Conformiſts)</hi> do.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="case">
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:160556:49"/>
               <head>CASE XIII. <hi>What are private Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans to do when things</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expedient <hi>are required of them?</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">Reſol.</head>
               <p>IN the fourth place, things <hi>enjoyned</hi> about the Worſhip of God may be ſuppoſed to be <hi>inexpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient</hi> when they are <hi>proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> unlawful.</p>
               <p>Here we have alſo aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, there is a farther abuſe of Authority that ought al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways to be limited by the <hi>Sacred Canons of Decency and Order,</hi> and things <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient;</hi> but admitting
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:160556:49"/> ſuch an <hi>unwarrantable</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erting of power, in requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring things that are <hi>lawful,</hi> but <hi>inexpedient;</hi> we are now to inquire how a <hi>private</hi> conſcience may preſerve it <hi>ſelf</hi> and the <hi>publick Peace,</hi> and whether it ſhould <hi>obey ſuch</hi> injunctions, or not.</p>
               <p>This is indeed the <hi>bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then;</hi> but how to remove it, <hi>hic labor, hoc opus eſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This, in the firſt place, ſeems to call us to <hi>another</hi> point of weighty <hi>moment, viz.</hi> Who is the <hi>proper Judge of expediency</hi> in the circumſtances of Gods Worſhip?</p>
               <p>There are but <hi>two</hi> that can bid for it; the <hi>publick</hi> prudence of lawfull Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, or our own <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate</hi> diſcretion: in things
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:160556:50"/> 
                  <hi>neceſſary,</hi> the <hi>Word</hi> of God is our <hi>Rule;</hi> in things <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient, Prudence:</hi> the Queſtion is, Whether <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate</hi> or <hi>publique?</hi> that is, (pardon my plainneſs) where God hath left the matter <hi>to men,</hi> whether the <hi>People</hi> or the <hi>Governours</hi> ſhould Rule? or, if you had rather, Whether they that are called to obey, are not bound to <hi>ſubmit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,</hi> where <hi>God</hi> himſelf <hi>interpoſeth</hi> not, <hi>to thoſe that have the Rule over them?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All, I know, will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, that when S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Paul</hi> had <hi>determined</hi> the decency and order of <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular</hi> things in the Church, that it would have been very <hi>Tumultuary</hi> for the <hi>people</hi> to have ſaid,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:160556:50"/> Theſe things ſeem ſtrange to us, and <hi>inexpedient:</hi> And the <hi>like</hi> cenſure would have paſſed upon thoſe, <hi>Act.</hi> 15. had they returned the like <hi>remora</hi> to the <hi>Synodical Sentence.</hi> Forgive me the wrong, Dear Reader, if I remember <hi>that</hi> of the <hi>Poet, Mutato nomine, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It may farther challenge a <hi>ſober</hi> debate, Whether the <hi>Ax<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> is not thus laid at the <hi>root</hi> of all polity and Government in the world, if once we grant the <hi>final Judgment</hi> of what is <hi>fit</hi> and orderly to <hi>private</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and that this ought to be the <hi>Rule</hi> of <hi>every</hi> ones practice.</p>
               <p>I muſt begg leave of the <hi>people</hi> to judge with <hi>Plato, Nullun ſenſus privatus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:160556:51"/> menſura eſt.</hi> I mean no more, but that every one is to judge what is <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary</hi> according to God; but <hi>publick</hi> Authority only what is <hi>expedient;</hi> and I think we have reaſon to adviſe, before we either give the things that are <hi>Gods,</hi> viz. <hi>neceſſary</hi> things, to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> or the things that are <hi>Caeſar's,</hi> that is, things <hi>expedient,</hi> to the <hi>people.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I do acknowledge the people a <hi>Judgment</hi> of <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcretion,</hi> the guide and meaſure of every ones acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>viz.</hi> to diſcern what <hi>God</hi> ſaith in things <hi>neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> and what <hi>humane Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> ſaith in things <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient,</hi> and to <hi>obey both;</hi> but for the people to be <hi>wiſe above what is written</hi>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:160556:51"/> in the Bible, to judge what is <hi>neceſsary,</hi> and what is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired by the <hi>Laws</hi> of the Land, to judge what is <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient,</hi> I fear is folly, and tends to <hi>confuſion</hi> in the Church and State.</p>
               <p>Where <hi>God</hi> commands and <hi>Man</hi> forbids; or where <hi>God</hi> forbids, and <hi>Man</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, we are bound by the Covenant of <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Grace</hi> to acknowledge the <hi>ſupremacy of heaven,</hi> and to obey <hi>God</hi> rather then <hi>Man:</hi> But where <hi>God</hi> is ſile<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t, and <hi>Man</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, <hi>Obedience to our Governours</hi> is far better (ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving more of Religion and Order in it) then <hi>ſacrifice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> to the <hi>net</hi> of our <hi>private</hi> Reaſon for things more expedient.</p>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:160556:52"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> having fixt by his own appointment all the <hi>Eſſentials</hi> of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Worſhip, left the <hi>Circumſtances</hi> of Decency and Order in the manner of performance, as things too ſmall to engage the Wiſedome of Heaven to the Church, as if there were ſome thing in this regard in that common ſaying, <hi>Non vacat exigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is rebus,</hi> &amp;c. Hereupon <hi>Calvin</hi> concludes, <hi>Haec in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differentia</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Inſt it. lib. 4, 7, 43.</note> 
                  <hi>ſunt, &amp; in Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae libertate poſita. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different</hi> things, things not decided by God, are left in the <hi>liberty</hi> of the Church: Not in the <hi>liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> of every <hi>Member;</hi> 'twere eaſie to ſhew, that was not <hi>Calvins</hi> meaning,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:160556:52"/> no more then it was the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> who denied that <hi>liberty</hi> to the <hi>people,</hi> and gave them <hi>particular</hi> Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders <hi>himſelf,</hi> then which there is nothing more evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in Scripture.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Conſulte agit qui praecep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to legis obtemperat,</hi> ſaith the <hi>Civilian:</hi> And no doubt when it is not <hi>ſin,</hi> 'tis wiſedom to <hi>obey</hi> the <hi>Law:</hi> It is ſeaſonable to call to <hi>mind</hi> and to <hi>practiſe</hi> too: <hi>Leges hominum, non homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes legum dominos eſſe opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tet:</hi> It is fitter that <hi>Laws</hi> ſhould govern <hi>Men,</hi> then that <hi>Men, private</hi> men, <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very</hi> private man ſhou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d govern the <hi>Laws:</hi> ſtill I muſt be underſtood in things <hi>not determined</hi> by <hi>God,</hi> for then we are <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obliged</hi>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:160556:53"/> by a <hi>higher</hi> Law, which ſuperſedes the <hi>low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er;</hi> and not <hi>we,</hi> but <hi>God</hi> contradicts ſuch <hi>Laws</hi> of <hi>Men</hi> as are againſt his <hi>own:</hi> But when the matter is left to <hi>Men,</hi> and they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand us; for us out of a pretended <hi>Judgment</hi> of <hi>diſcretion,</hi> to object <hi>incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience</hi> and <hi>inexpedience,</hi> and to reſiſt the power, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours but little of either Judgment or Diſcretion.</p>
               <p>But, that I may offer all <hi>fair</hi> ſatisfaction to this <hi>great</hi> ſcruple, I crave leave to admit the <hi>private</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience into the <hi>Chair,</hi> and then the <hi>Caſe</hi> ſtands thus.</p>
               <div type="case">
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:160556:53"/>
                  <head>CASE. <hi>Whether any thing that in our</hi> private <hi>judgment is</hi> unfit <hi>and inconvenient to be uſed in the exerciſe of Religion, may be</hi> warran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably <hi>practiſed by us when</hi> commanded <hi>there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto by Authority?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <head type="sub">Reſol.</head>
                  <p>I Would be very far from the guilt of winding the conſcience of the <hi>plain</hi> Reader into any <hi>needleſs</hi> intricacy in this <hi>practical</hi> Caſe; yet I muſt preſume a little upon him, to make way for my Anſwer here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, by a <hi>few plain diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <pb n="82" facs="tcp:160556:54"/> 1. There is a fitneſs or expedience with reſpect to <hi>Governours</hi> or <hi>private</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; <hi>their</hi> command or <hi>our</hi> obedience: whence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe two great Caſes, that muſt be diſtinguiſhed and not confounded; 1. What is fit for <hi>Authority</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire? 2. What is fit <hi>for us</hi> to do?</p>
                  <p>No queſtion, our <hi>Rulers</hi> may poſſibly require that which is <hi>not fit</hi> to be requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; and conſequently, that which they <hi>ought not</hi> to require: and <hi>ſuch</hi> their impoſitions may be <hi>ſinfull</hi> as to <hi>them;</hi> which yet I doubt not may be <hi>lawfull</hi> and fit <hi>for us.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Whether Rulers exert their power in things <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different</hi> as they ought, or
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:160556:54"/> not, I judge, more imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately concerns the <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> of <hi>Rulers,</hi> rather then of us <hi>private</hi> perſons: with us, the great and next and moſt concerning Caſe is this; Not ſo much what Rulers may require; as what we may do; or rather, not ſo much what it is fit for <hi>them</hi> to <hi>impoſe,</hi> as what is fit for <hi>us</hi> to <hi>do.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. There is again a fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or expediency <hi>quoad rem,</hi> and <hi>quoad nos:</hi> Or more plainly, <hi>fitneſs</hi> is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable in a more <hi>large</hi> and general ſence, as <hi>applied</hi> to its <hi>ſubject,</hi> that is, to the Service that is to be performed, without any farther conſidering of any other circumſtances of it; as the fitneſs of <hi>kneeling,</hi>
                     <pb n="84" facs="tcp:160556:55"/> 
                     <hi>ſtanding</hi> or <hi>ſitting</hi> at the Sacrament: or in a more <hi>ſtrict</hi> and qualified applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to my <hi>particular</hi> acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>kneeling, ſtanding</hi> or <hi>ſitting,</hi> &amp;c. as it is accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with all the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances and intangle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of my <hi>private</hi> Caſe.</p>
                  <p>And thus we diſcover <hi>two</hi> Caſes more: Whether in <hi>general</hi> &amp; <hi>quoadrem,</hi> or according to the nature of the thing to do this or that; <hi>e. g.</hi> to receive the Sacrament <hi>kneeling,</hi> or <hi>ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,</hi> or <hi>ſtanding?</hi> or 2<hi rend="sup">dly</hi>, What is fitteſt for <hi>us to do,</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l the <hi>circumſtances</hi> and obligations of our pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate and particular Caſes firſt <hi>duely</hi> pondered? for I little doubt, but that at length it will ſufficiently
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:160556:55"/> appear, that that which is not ſo fit in <hi>it ſelf,</hi> may yet be expedient for <hi>us</hi> to do: And therefore give me leave once again to ſtate you the Queſtion thus.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="case">
                  <head>CASE. <hi>Whether, if Authority re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire that which is</hi> law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>in it ſelf, but not</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient, <hi>all things conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, it may not be both</hi> lawfull <hi>and</hi> expedient <hi>to obey and do it?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <head type="sub">Reſol.</head>
                  <p>THere is nothing more plain &amp; certain, then that the <hi>ſame</hi> lawful things, at divers times and to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:160556:56"/> perſons, were judged by the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> to be both <hi>expedient</hi> and <hi>inexpedient,</hi> both in his <hi>doctrine</hi> and <hi>practice;</hi> who became a <hi>Jew</hi> to the <hi>Jews,</hi> and a <hi>Grecian</hi> to the <hi>Grecians;</hi> and even all <hi>things</hi> to all <hi>men,</hi> that he might win <hi>ſome.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Upon the like ground <hi>Ambroſe, Auguſtine,</hi> &amp;c. held that <hi>expedient</hi> for themſelves and others to practiſe in <hi>one</hi> Church, which they judged altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>unfit</hi> in <hi>another</hi> of a different <hi>uſage.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now what ſhould be the <hi>reaſon</hi> of this <hi>mutabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity</hi> of Indifferent things? This <hi>well</hi> purſued will car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry us farr towards a ſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this great difficulty.</p>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:160556:56"/>
                  <p> No doubt <hi>Polanus</hi> hit u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon it, whoſe words are <hi>weighty</hi> and juſtly worthy of <hi>all acceptation</hi> by ſuch as deſire ſatisfaction about the <hi>nature</hi> and <hi>uſe,</hi> the <hi>fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> or <hi>unfitneſs</hi> of things <hi>Indifferent.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Adiaphorae res ſunt lici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Polan. tom. 2. pag. 376.</note> 
                     <hi>vel illicitae pro circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiarum ratione:</hi> Things Indifferent (ſaith he) are lawfull or unlawfull, by reaſon of their <hi>circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances;</hi> for which he cites <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 20, 21. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. 13. But, put caſe that circumſtances <hi>allow</hi> or <hi>diſſwade</hi> on <hi>both</hi> ſides; that there are either <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniences</hi> to deterr, or <hi>advantages</hi> to invite on both ſides; What is to be done in ſuch a caſe? <hi>Polanus</hi>
                     <pb n="88" facs="tcp:160556:57"/> therefore adds, <hi>Hîc autem in Circumſtantiarum pugnâ &amp; contrarietate; minoris momenti, iis quae major is momenti, pauciores pluribus cedant:</hi> i. e. Where there is a conteſt and contrarie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of circumſtances, thoſe that are <hi>leſs</hi> in weight and <hi>fewer</hi> in number muſt give way to thoſe that are <hi>grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> and <hi>more,</hi> Rom. 14. 21.</p>
                  <p>So that, would you know, whether it be fit to <hi>obey</hi> Authority in things that are <hi>lawfull</hi> be <hi>inexpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient,</hi> bring the <hi>Caſe</hi> to the <hi>Teſt.</hi> Where is the <hi>over-ballance</hi> of expedience and fitneſs? Conſider &amp; weigh the Circumſtances on both ſides, and examine whether to follow our <hi>own judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> and diſobey Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:160556:57"/> in an <hi>inconvenience,</hi> or to do that which is incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient <hi>in obedience</hi> to Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, be really attended with the more or fewer, the greater or leſs <hi>inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences. I ſpeak as unto wiſe men, judge ye what I ſay,</hi> and anſwer your ſelves.</p>
                  <p>Yet, that I may miniſter all my <hi>aſſiſtance</hi> to my Readers <hi>Conſcience,</hi> let us in earneſt put the queſtion, Whether the <hi>Conveniences</hi> of Obedience in ſuch a caſe may not greatly <hi>over-bear</hi> the <hi>expediency</hi> of the thing required?</p>
                  <p>Truely, in my moſt ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous pondering of this weighty matter, there are three things of ſo great concern, &amp; even <hi>indiſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:160556:58"/> conveniency,</hi> if I may ſo undervalue them that offer their attendance to <hi>ſuch</hi> an <hi>Obedience,</hi> that the <hi>ordinary</hi> inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of any <hi>lawfull</hi> thing injoined ſeems very <hi>light</hi> and inconſiderable to them; the very <hi>mention</hi> of them, one would think, is of weight ſufficient to ſway the <hi>ballance:</hi> they are <hi>Peace, Duty, Safety;</hi> in the behalf of each of theſe, we ſhall venture to engage a <hi>particular com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:160556:58"/>
                  <head>Sect. 1. <hi>Of Peace.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>VVHen we muſt either <hi>conform</hi> to an <hi>inexpedient indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent</hi> thing; or by our <hi>non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformity</hi> break or but ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard the <hi>peace,</hi> let ſuch as have been <hi>ſcorch't</hi> in the flames of <hi>contention,</hi> or car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie about them the <hi>skarrs</hi> of <hi>Warr,</hi> or have any way learn'd to <hi>value</hi> peace, judge what is to be done.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>PEACE</hi> (as the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turaliſts ſay of the <hi>Radical Moiſture)</hi> is the <hi>Root</hi> of althings; but by the <hi>heats</hi> of trouble and publique contention, (alas!) how ſoon does our glory and
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:160556:59"/> goodlineſs <hi>wither,</hi> and all proſperity <hi>die</hi> away? Who trembles not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>at the <hi>thought,</hi> yea at the very <hi>motion</hi> towards a thought, of being guilty of throw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the leaſt <hi>brand</hi> into this fire; leſt (as a Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Divine addes) he ſhould be made a <hi>firebrand in hell?</hi> Say not, Thy <hi>particular,</hi> or thy <hi>partie</hi> is inconſiderable; a <hi>spark</hi> unthought of, unſeen, and almoſt inviſible, turns a <hi>City</hi> into aſhes: How <hi>great a matter a little fire kindles!</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Therefore ſaith one, <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cut vita in homine, ita pax</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Aqui.</hi> in <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.</note> 
                     <hi>in regno, &amp;c. Peace</hi> in a Kingdom is as <hi>life</hi> in a man: and as health is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but a <hi>temper</hi> of the
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:160556:59"/> humors, ſo there is <hi>Peace</hi> where every thing keeps its <hi>own Order;</hi> and as when <hi>health</hi> fails, the man tends to <hi>death;</hi> ſo when <hi>Peace</hi> departs, a Kingdom tends to <hi>deſolation;</hi> whence the great and laſt intention, is, to keep the <hi>Peace.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>O that men would a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle conſider; what do they loſe by doing that which they judge <hi>inexpedient,</hi> if it be lawful? Not <hi>Peace</hi> with <hi>God,</hi> he hath not forbidden it; not <hi>Peace of Conſcience,</hi> that allows it; not <hi>Peace</hi> with <hi>Authority,</hi> that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands it. What then? A little <hi>pleaſing of our ſelves,</hi> a ſmall portion of private ſatisfaction, and the enjoyment of our <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty</hi> in a thing <hi>indifferent,</hi>
                     <pb n="94" facs="tcp:160556:60"/> becauſe we judge it not to <hi>be expedient.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Again, Oh that it were well conſidered, what is <hi>loſt</hi> with the <hi>Peace</hi> of the Church, what we hazard when we hazard this.</p>
                  <p>Ah! what convenience is offered to ballance the <hi>neceſſity</hi> of <hi>Peace?</hi> what can ſatisfie the <hi>loſs</hi> of Peace? where is our <hi>liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> when <hi>Peace</hi> is gone? how dreadful are the fruits of <hi>Contentions?</hi> who ſails to the <hi>Indies</hi> in hopes of a <hi>peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple;</hi> or would venture all in the hazard of ſo neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry a thing as <hi>Peace,</hi> for ſo ſmall a matter as his <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate</hi> content in a <hi>bare ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediency?</hi> Can this <hi>expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency</hi> that we deſire <hi>warrant</hi> us againſt all the <hi>Precepts,</hi>
                     <pb n="95" facs="tcp:160556:60"/> perſwaſions, beſeechings of the God of Peace, to <hi>pray</hi> for, <hi>ſtudy, ſeek, purſue,</hi> and <hi>follow</hi> after peace? Can this defend us from the <hi>threatnings</hi> denounced a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>troublers</hi> of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael?</hi> or make up the loſs of all the comforts of the <hi>ſons</hi> of <hi>Peace,</hi> and the <hi>bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſs</hi> promiſed to <hi>peace-makers?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Yea, let it be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, whether in things In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different, if there be any <hi>hazard</hi> of the <hi>peace</hi> of the Church one way or other; the queſtion muſt not be ſo much, What is expedient, and what not; but <hi>What makes for peace,</hi> and what not: And if this be the caſe indeed with us, let that weighty advice of
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:160556:61"/> the bleſſed <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſink deep into our <hi>conſcience,</hi> and <hi>decide</hi> the Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie; which if ſincerely heeded, it being ſo <hi>through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> fitted to this very caſe, I dare be bold to ſay, muſt needs do it. <hi>Let us follow after the things that make</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 13</note> 
                     <hi>for peace;</hi> q. d. in theſe indifferent things (of which he was treating) trouble not your ſelvs <hi>over-much:</hi> ſome may think <hi>this</hi> expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient, ſome <hi>that;</hi> but in theſe things, let me per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade you to make <hi>peace</hi> your <hi>Rule;</hi> and while o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, with too much hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, enflame their contentions, about what is <hi>fitteſt,</hi> to the <hi>breach</hi> of the <hi>peace,</hi> and the trouble of the Church; be you ſure, to <hi>mark</hi> thoſe
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:160556:61"/> things that <hi>make for peace,</hi> and follow them. Flie contention, and too much ſcrupiloſity in ſuch things, and <hi>follow after things which make for peace.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Upon the <hi>like</hi> grounds, no doubt, St <hi>Auguſtine</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived that grave advice of St <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> as if it had been an <hi>Oracle, To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form to the Uſages of every Church where he came, as he would neither take nor give offence.</hi> St <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Epiſt. 118.</note> alſo gives the like ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice upon ſomewhat the like reaſon; <hi>for the ſake of the Society of thoſe, with whom we live.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That which <hi>Beza</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports of <hi>Calvin</hi> is very remarkable. In <hi>Calvins</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Bez.</hi> in vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. <hi>Calv.</hi>
                     </note> abſence, it ſeems, the <hi>Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer-cake</hi>
                     <pb n="98" facs="tcp:160556:62"/> was brought into the <hi>Sacrament</hi> at <hi>Geneva:</hi> now, though <hi>Calvin</hi> judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it very <hi>inconvenient,</hi> yet he judged the <hi>peace</hi> more <hi>needfull,</hi> and did earneſtly admoniſh them not to be <hi>contentious</hi> about a thing <hi>indifferent.</hi> And in ſo good a temper his words took them, that they, both <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters</hi> and <hi>People,</hi> ſo lowed his Counſel.</p>
                  <p>This was nothing but the <hi>Application</hi> of that <hi>General Rule</hi> which <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin</hi> commended to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians in his <hi>own</hi> writings, with which we ſhall <hi>ſeal</hi> up this particular: Though <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Calv.</hi> Epiſt 379.</note> a thing (ſaith he) be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, ſhould <hi>bring offence, and draw ill conſequences with it,</hi> (that is, be <hi>inexpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient)</hi>
                     <pb n="99" facs="tcp:160556:62"/> yet if in <hi>it ſelf</hi> it be not repugnant to <hi>Gods Word,</hi> it may be yielded unto, eſpecially where the <hi>greater</hi> part prevaileth; in which he is but a <hi>member</hi> of that <hi>body,</hi> and can pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed <hi>no farther:</hi> and by conſequence<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <hi>non-conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> would hazard <hi>peace.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. 2. <hi>Of Duty.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THe <hi>ſecond</hi> thing that lies in <hi>ſcale</hi> againſt the <hi>Inexpediency</hi> of things impoſed, is that weighty thing called <hi>D<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>TY.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Here there ſeems to be ſo much <hi>odds,</hi> that the Queſtion is no longer what we <hi>may</hi> do, or what is <hi>fit</hi> for us to do, but what
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:160556:63"/> we <hi>muſt:</hi> So that <hi>may</hi> is over-weighed by <hi>muſt, fit</hi> by <hi>juſt, liberty</hi> and <hi>expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency</hi> by <hi>duty</hi> and <hi>neceſſity,</hi> with reſpect to <hi>God</hi> and to the <hi>Magiſtrate.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. There is a <hi>muſt</hi> from <hi>God;</hi> a <hi>neceſſity laid upon us</hi> from heaven, and <hi>wo</hi> be to <hi>Miniſters</hi> if they <hi>preach</hi> not the <hi>Goſpel;</hi> and <hi>wo</hi> be to the <hi>people</hi> if they <hi>attend</hi> not the <hi>Ordinances;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, the <hi>neceſſity</hi> of <hi>obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience</hi> to Magiſtrates on both.</p>
                  <p>But now there is no muſt <hi>not</hi> perform ſuch <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different</hi> things, as we ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple at for their <hi>inexpedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency;</hi> yet, we fear, that ſo it may happen, that <hi>refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing</hi> to obey Authority in ſuch <hi>indifferent</hi> things, may
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:160556:63"/> incapacitate us for the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of thoſe neceſſary <hi>duties, neceſſàry</hi> with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to <hi>Gods</hi> command, and the <hi>great ſalvation</hi> of immortal ſouls:</p>
                  <p>This very conſideration turned the ſcale in that old but moſt Eminent <hi>Non-Conformiſt</hi> T. C. his judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <note place="margin">Third Book.</note> 
                     <hi>long agon</hi> about the Surplice. <q>The truth is, faith he, (though in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Book of his before he had called the <hi>Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plice</hi> a <hi>Mark and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Popiſh Abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion)</hi> I dare not be Author to any to forſake his <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoral Charge</hi> for the <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenience;</hi> and giveth this very Reaſon, Becauſe <hi>Preaching</hi> is the <hi>abſolute command</hi> of God, and
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:160556:64"/> therefore ought not to be laid aſide for a <hi>ſimple inconvenience</hi> or uncom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs of a thing which in its nature is <hi>indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. There is a <hi>muſt</hi> alſo from man. Our Rulers, under God, do alſo give us our <hi>Care of Souls,</hi> which we accept from them; they command us to <hi>Preach,</hi> and <hi>feed the Flock:</hi> they laſtly injoyn us to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe our <hi>duty</hi> with ſuch and ſuch <hi>circumſtances,</hi> which they judge moſt <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient: God</hi> alſo adds <hi>his</hi> command, that we ſhould for <hi>conſcience ſake,</hi> yea, for <hi>his own ſake (Magiſtrates</hi> being <hi>his</hi> Vice-gerents) <hi>ſubmit our ſelves to every Ordinance of man,</hi> that is
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:160556:64"/> not contrary to the <hi>Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now this is the very Caſe: and ſurely it muſt be a <hi>very great</hi> inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, attending a <hi>circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance</hi> of our <hi>duty,</hi> that can out-weigh our <hi>duty;</hi> our duty to <hi>God,</hi> to our <hi>Prince,</hi> to our <hi>Places,</hi> to our <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences,</hi> and to the <hi>ſouls</hi> of the people.</p>
                  <p>Let me humbly enter this <hi>caveat,</hi> take heed of reſiſting the <hi>Ordinance of God</hi> while you contemn a humane Inſtitution. The Ordinance of <hi>Man</hi> may be <hi>inconvenient;</hi> but reſiſting the Ordinance of <hi>God</hi> is plainly <hi>ſinful,</hi> and ſadly at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall therefore com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend the <hi>fatherly</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:160556:65"/> of <hi>Auguſtine</hi> unto you, and therewith alſo <hi>ſeal</hi> up this Particular. <q>In thoſe <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Aug.</hi> Ep. 86.</note> things (ſaith he) in which the <hi>holy Scripture</hi> hath made no <hi>certain</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment, let the <hi>cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom</hi> of the people of God, or <hi>inſtituta majo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> the injunctions of Governors, be held for a <hi>Law.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. 3. <hi>Of Safety.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THe <hi>laſt</hi> great conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niency that I ſhall leave in the <hi>ballance</hi> againſt the expediency deſired and ſtuck upon, is that of <hi>Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> and <hi>Preſervation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Beſides our <hi>own,</hi> which haply we <hi>little regard,</hi> the
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:160556:65"/> 
                     <hi>ſafety</hi> of our <hi>party,</hi> which we may too <hi>much</hi> value, the ſafety of the <hi>people,</hi> their <hi>great ſalvation,</hi> yea, the very concern of <hi>Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and the <hi>power</hi> of Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; theſe, no doubt, are things of <hi>weight</hi> with all <hi>prudent</hi> and good men.</p>
                  <p>But I humbly requeſt, my <hi>diſcontented</hi> Brethren, May not <hi>ſuch</hi> things as theſe, theſe very things, yea, all theſe things be <hi>ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarded</hi> by <hi>checking</hi> at <hi>obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience</hi> in things <hi>inexpedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent,</hi> barely inexpedient?</p>
                  <p>Do not you <hi>fear?</hi> do not you <hi>ſay</hi> that you cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly fore ſee, that you al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready begin to <hi>feel</hi> the loſs of your intereſt in a graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>KING,</hi> in the <hi>Laws</hi> of the Land, the laying
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:160556:66"/> down of the <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> and the committing of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious ſouls of your poor people to the <hi>care,</hi> or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>neglect</hi> of a <hi>blind</hi> and ſottiſh, careleſs and <hi>ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous Miniſtry?</hi> Is there nothing in theſe, <hi>in all of theſe,</hi> can <hi>recompence</hi> the loſs of a bare <hi>expediency,</hi> or the trouble of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary? God forbid.</p>
                  <p>Do not you <hi>fear,</hi> (for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give my plainneſs) do you not <hi>ſay</hi> you <hi>fear</hi> that your <hi>Non-conformity</hi> may tempt the <hi>Conformiſts</hi> to lean to <hi>Popery</hi> for ſupport? If ſo, my Brethren, (though o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers fear it not) may not this endanger the <hi>Church</hi> of God among us, yea, all the <hi>Reformed</hi> Churches in the world, (which may
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:160556:66"/> ſomewhat depend upon <hi>ours)</hi> to be ſwallowed up by the <hi>Common Enemy?</hi> Is this the caſe, my brethren? do you indeed judge it ſo? and will you be at <hi>no trouble</hi> to <hi>ſave</hi> them? will you part with no <hi>convenience,</hi> to preſerve them? is your own content and private liberty, in ſo <hi>ſmall</hi> a matter, of <hi>greater</hi> moment then all the <hi>Churches?</hi> Alas! had our <hi>LORD</hi> vallued them at no higher rate, they <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Certum e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>, omnia li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere pro Patria</hi> Quintill.</note> had hardly been the <hi>pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe</hi> of his Precious <hi>BLOOD.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>What <hi>hope</hi> of expedien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy can repair the danger? yea, what expediency, <hi>if obtained?</hi> which yet is but our aim, and can hardly be ſecured in the <hi>accident,</hi> if
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:160556:67"/> the <hi>ſubſtance</hi> miſcarry; our admired <hi>expediency</hi> being <hi>equally hazarded</hi> by our <hi>Non-conformity</hi> with all the reſt, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Peace</hi> of the Church, our <hi>duty</hi> to God and Man, the favour of the <hi>King,</hi> the <hi>Goſpel</hi> of Chriſt, the <hi>ſervice</hi> of the Church, the <hi>ſalvation</hi> of ſouls, the ſafety of the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Cauſe in the World.</p>
                  <p>Who can ſo fondly ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine that the God of all <hi>theſe</hi> can have any regard to the <hi>loan Sacrifice</hi> of our expediency, with ſo much <hi>prodigality,</hi> ſo little regard to <hi>mercy</hi> and charity, and ſuch dreadful <hi>hazards?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But to bring it cloſer to our ſelves; I doubt not to affirm, that our own <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:160556:67"/> ſafety,</hi> the ſafety of our perſons, our <hi>families</hi> and <hi>eſtates,</hi> may juſtly challenge ſome influence, <hi>when concerned,</hi> upon our <hi>conformity</hi> in <hi>lawful</hi> things, though ſomewhat <hi>inexpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient.</hi> But ſeeing ſo many are preparing themſelves to <hi>glory</hi> in ſuch kind of <hi>ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings,</hi> though attended with all the <hi>hazards</hi> lately named, we ſhall put the Caſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="case">
                  <pb n="110" facs="tcp:160556:68"/>
                  <head>CASE. <hi>Whether is it</hi> fit <hi>or</hi> lawful <hi>to expoſe our ſelves and ours to ſufferings, rather then</hi> conform <hi>in things</hi> lawful <hi>but</hi> inexpedient?</head>
                  <head type="sub">Reſol.</head>
                  <p>TRuly to me it ſeemeth a ſtrange <hi>prodigality,</hi> neither <hi>fit</hi> nor <hi>lawful,</hi> but more, far more unfit and <hi>inexpedient</hi> then the very things that are ſcrupled at, be they very <hi>inexpedient,</hi> as ſome conceive, if they be but <hi>lawful.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In ſuch kind of ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings to me appeareth <hi>little</hi> or <hi>no good,</hi> but <hi>much evil.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. I ſee but little <hi>good</hi>
                     <pb n="111" facs="tcp:160556:68"/> in them, becauſe I can find no <hi>call</hi> unto them.</p>
                  <p>We are indeed invited to <hi>hazard,</hi> yea, to <hi>ſuffer</hi> the <hi>loſs</hi> and <hi>pain</hi> of a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l things for Chriſt his ſake, and the Goſpels, and for Righteouſneſs ſake; this is, for the <hi>Teſtimony of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus;</hi> this is the one thing <hi>neceſſary;</hi> all other things are <hi>not neceſſary</hi> in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon, in competition with this: Alas! this is far from a bare expediency; 'tis the <hi>ſubſtance,</hi> and more then the Accidents and Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances that God calls us to ſuffer for.</p>
                  <p>If we ſuffer for things <hi>expedient,</hi> we ſuffer for our own apprehenſion of what is ſo, and not for the <hi>Word</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> that hath left it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decided
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:160556:69"/> what is ſo; and conſequently, what ever we tempt our ſelves with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, ſuch Suffering is far from <hi>Martyrdome,</hi> which lies in the <hi>Cauſe,</hi> as well as the <hi>Occaſion</hi> and <hi>Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>We find no <hi>command</hi> requiring, no <hi>example</hi> of Chriſt, his Prophets of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles foregoing, no <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes</hi> encouraging us in ſuch <hi>kind</hi> of ſuffering; and how then can we expect a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>comfort</hi> in them, <hi>ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port</hi> under them, or <hi>reward</hi> for them?</p>
                  <p>Yea, do not we meet with a <hi>check</hi> to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, for ſuch zeal and forwardneſs, from a <hi>pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent</hi> perſon? <hi>Be not righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous over-much; why ſhouldſt</hi>
                     <pb n="113" facs="tcp:160556:69"/> 
                     <hi>thou deſtroy thy ſelf before thy time?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. As little good, ſo, <hi>much evil</hi> appears in them: for ſuch cauſleſs <hi>call-leſs</hi> ſufferings injure <hi>God,</hi> the <hi>Church,</hi> our <hi>ſelves.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>God,</hi> on whom we father our <hi>private</hi> opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for which we ſuffer, as if they were his <hi>Cauſe;</hi> u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurping alſo the <hi>honour</hi> and dignity of <hi>ſuffering for Chriſt,</hi> which he hath not yet given us.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The <hi>Church,</hi> thus denying her our <hi>Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> putting our <hi>candle</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a <hi>buſhel,</hi> or being <hi>thieves</hi> to her <hi>light; sempting</hi> the <hi>weak</hi> that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand not our Reaſons, to ſuffer with us without a cauſe; and doing our part
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:160556:70"/> to make <hi>ſuch breaches,</hi> and to raiſe ſuch a <hi>ſtorm</hi> as may <hi>ſhipwrack</hi> all.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Our Selves;</hi> from whom, as one ſays, God calls for the <hi>calves of our lips,</hi> but we offer him our <hi>lives,</hi> our <hi>liberties,</hi> our <hi>wives,</hi> our <hi>children, &amp;c.</hi> before he requi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es them at our hands; wherein I trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to put it to a queſtion, Whether there be more of <hi>Martyrdome</hi> or <hi>Murther.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If my advice be any thing to be regarded, rather obey as far as <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Conſcience</hi> will permit; and when they check you, <hi>ſuffer,</hi> and ſuffer <hi>cheerfully;</hi> ſuffer for <hi>God,</hi> ſuffer for <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and ſuffer <hi>comfortably;</hi> but if you ſtop your courſe of obedience before <hi>God</hi> call
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:160556:70"/> 
                     <hi>&amp; conſcience</hi> checks, be your <hi>private</hi> reaſons what they can, I think there is cauſe to fear leſt ſuch <hi>haſty</hi> ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings are of <hi>your</hi> ſelves, and rather <hi>puniſhments</hi> of your inconſiderateneſs and diſobedience, then any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of <hi>Martyrdom.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Give me leave to end in <hi>plainneſs,</hi> as dealing with <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and aiming at the <hi>ſafety</hi> of my Brethren. If we throw away the <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents</hi> that God hath lent us, and pay him in <hi>Coin</hi> he will not own, he may juſtly ſend us, for our wages, to thoſe we have ſerved, our <hi>evil ſurmiſes</hi> (I ſpeak it ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berly) and the jealouſies and <hi>fears</hi> of our <hi>brethren.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>'Tis plain, that a promiſe of outward proſperity
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:160556:71"/> gives juſt encouragement for obedience to Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; <hi>Honour thy Father and thy Mother, that thy days may be long upon the Land which the Lord thy God giveth thee.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="case">
               <head>CASE XIV. <hi>What are private perſons to do, when things</hi> ſinful <hi>are impoſed?</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">Reſol.</head>
               <p>I Would not be miſtaken, I have not hitherto in, and I truſt never ſhall be an <hi>Advocate</hi> for <hi>ſin</hi> or ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful impoſitions; I have on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pleaded for a juſt and <hi>peaceable</hi> ſelf-denial, and
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:160556:71"/> ſubmiſſion to the <hi>Laws</hi> of the <hi>Place</hi> where we live, in <hi>lawful things:</hi> We are deſcending to the loweſt ſtep from things <hi>Neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Expedient, purely In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different,</hi> and <hi>Inexpedient,</hi> (all which have had their <hi>particular</hi> debate) to the <hi>laſt</hi> object of impoſition propoſed, <hi>viz. Things un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful;</hi> to conſider what we are to do, ſhould Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority require conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in <hi>things unlawful.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That I may ſpeak fully, and as I humbly deſire, <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactorily,</hi> to this doubt, I ſhall take the <hi>liberty</hi> of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction.</p>
               <p>Things are <hi>ſinful,</hi> either,</p>
               <p n="1">1. In themſelves, <hi>viz.</hi> ſuch as God prohibits.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Or, <hi>To us,</hi> ſuch as we
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:160556:72"/> judge to be forbidden of God. Or,</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Unto others,</hi> ſuch as <hi>others</hi> judge to be <hi>ſinful,</hi> when they are neither ſo <hi>in themſelves,</hi> nor judged ſo by <hi>us</hi> that are to uſe them; according to which diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution we are further invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the conſideration of <hi>three</hi> Caſes.</p>
               <p n="1">1. What we are to doe when things ſinful in themſelves are required. Or,</p>
               <p n="2">2. When ſuch things are required as <hi>appear</hi> ſinful to <hi>our ſelves.</hi> Or,</p>
               <p n="3">3. If not to our ſelves, <hi>to others</hi> that will be offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded at our obedience.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="case">
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:160556:72"/>
               <head>CASE I. <hi>What are we to do when things of themſelves and</hi> materially evil <hi>are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by Authority?</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">Reſol.</head>
               <p>ST <hi>Auguſtine</hi> delivered <hi>much</hi> in thoſe <hi>few</hi> words, <hi>There can be no Law that is not juſt.</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Bernard</hi> gives us a ſmart explicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and account of it; <hi>What man commands,</hi> in ſuch a caſe, <hi>God forbids,</hi> and ſo repeals and nuls it; or rather by a pre-declaring his <hi>Will</hi> againſt it, <hi>by whom Kings Reign,</hi> it is void of it ſelf <hi>ipſo facto.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hereupon the concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:160556:73"/> is drawn home to our <hi>preſent</hi> Caſe in the other words of <hi>Bernard; Pura</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ber.</hi> Ep. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>mala ut nunquam juſte ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beri, ſic nec licite poſſunt f<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eri;</hi> Things of themſelves and materially evil, as they cannot be juſtly command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſo they may not be <hi>law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully</hi> done.</p>
               <p>Shall we be deaf to <hi>God</hi> (as <hi>Bernard</hi> reaſons) and hear <hi>Men?</hi> or with the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, ſhall we <hi>hearken</hi> to <hi>men</hi> rather then <hi>God?</hi> We muſt not obey a <hi>Conſtable</hi> in oppoſition to the <hi>King;</hi> nor the <hi>King</hi> in oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to <hi>God,</hi> the King of <hi>Kings,</hi> as well as <hi>Subjects,</hi> and the King of <hi>Subjects</hi> as well as <hi>Kings,</hi> whoſe Soveraign <hi>Authority both</hi> Kings and Subjects and all
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:160556:73"/> muſt acknowledge, leſt he vindicate it with his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="case">
               <head>CASE II. <hi>What are we to do when ſuch things 'are required, as, if</hi> not ſinful <hi>in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, yet</hi> we <hi>judge to be</hi> ſo?</head>
               <head type="sub">Reſol.</head>
               <p>IT is paſt denial, that as ſome things may ſeem lawful to one that ſeem <hi>ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful</hi> to another; ſo, ſome things may ſeem either <hi>lawful</hi> when they are <hi>ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful,</hi> or <hi>ſinful</hi> when they are <hi>lawful,</hi> to perſons <hi>miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>informed.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="122" facs="tcp:160556:74"/>
               <p> Therefore, where a thing <hi>ſeems lawful</hi> to our <hi>Rulers,</hi> and fit to be impoſed, and yet <hi>we</hi> judge it <hi>ſinful,</hi> and not to be performed. The advice I ſhould tender in <hi>ſuch</hi> a caſe, is,</p>
               <p>Firſt, Be not <hi>over-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident</hi> of the certainty of thine own opinion, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering others, eſpecially men in <hi>Authority,</hi> that with advice and aſſiſtances, which <hi>private</hi> perſons can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not obtain, have judged it not only <hi>lawful,</hi> but <hi>fit</hi> to be impoſed and practiſed: and perhaps if thou haſt u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed any due <hi>diligence</hi> for the diſcovery of the truth herein, thou haſt ſeen <hi>rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> to be more <hi>favourable</hi> in thy <hi>cenſure</hi> then for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly.</p>
               <pb n="123" facs="tcp:160556:74"/>
               <p> 2. Therefore, with <hi>ſelf-diffidence</hi> ſearch farther, ſearch impartially, read on both ſides; if any thing <hi>bias</hi> thee, let it be thy mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt of thy <hi>ſelf,</hi> thy <hi>eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of others,</hi> thy inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to <hi>peace,</hi> thy love of the <hi>Church,</hi> thy <hi>obedience</hi> to ſuperiors; ever remembring, that <hi>ignorance</hi> and <hi>preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice</hi> make <hi>ſnares</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, and <hi>Zeal</hi> without <hi>Knowledge</hi> ſets the Church on <hi>fire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>3. When thou haſt <hi>tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly</hi> ſearched, the matter muſt needs appear unto thee either <hi>lawful,</hi> or <hi>doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful,</hi> or <hi>ſinful</hi> ſtill.</p>
               <p n="1">1. If <hi>God</hi> ſhall bleſs thy endeavours with <hi>conviction,</hi> and bring thee to ſee thine own errour, and the <hi>law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs</hi>
                  <pb n="124" facs="tcp:160556:75"/> of that which before thou <hi>condemnedſt,</hi> the <hi>ground</hi> of the doubt is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, and conſequently <hi>Obedience</hi> is <hi>juſtly</hi> expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from thee.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If thy labours for ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction have only brought thee into ſome <hi>farther ſuſpition</hi> of thy o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, ſo that now it doth not ſeem to be <hi>directly</hi> ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful which is required, but of a doubtful nature, ſo that thou art in a doubt whether thou maiſt <hi>obey</hi> or <hi>not,</hi> I commend thee for thy <hi>further</hi> ſatisfaction, to that excellent <hi>Caſuiſt</hi> the Reverend Biſhop of <hi>Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coln</hi> his Lectures, <hi>p.</hi> 216. <hi>&amp;</hi> 217.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>He concludes, If be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of ſome <hi>probable</hi>
                     <pb n="125" facs="tcp:160556:75"/> reaſons, appearing on both ſides, the <hi>ſubject</hi> cannot eaſily determine with himſelf whether the <hi>Law</hi> be right or not, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that his mind is in a great <hi>incertainty,</hi> and knows not which way to incline; he is bound in this caſe actually to <hi>obey</hi> it; ſo that he ſinneth if he obeyeth it not, and doth not ſin if he obeyeth.</q> For which he gives ſeveral Reaſons.</p>
               <p>In general, the Reaſon ſeems to be this; That whereof a man <hi>doubts</hi> holds the <hi>beam,</hi> as it were, <hi>even;</hi> there is equal weight in each <hi>ſcale:</hi> ſo we ſay, A man doubting is one in <hi>bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vio,</hi> in <hi>aequilibrio;</hi> but if the command of <hi>Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi>
                  <pb n="112" facs="tcp:160556:76"/> be thrown into the <hi>ſcale,</hi> it muſt needs turn it, if <hi>even</hi> before: this may not draw me to think it <hi>more lawful,</hi> but yet more <hi>neceſſary;</hi> not more law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful with reſpect to <hi>God,</hi> yet more lawful with reſpect to <hi>us,</hi> and more practica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; upon that known rule, <hi>In re dubia,</hi> &amp;c. In a doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful caſe the <hi>ſafer part</hi> is to be choſen.</p>
               <p n="3">3. But if the thing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired appear <hi>ſinful</hi> to thee <hi>ſtill,</hi> thou art bound by the <hi>Law,</hi> thou art bound to the <hi>peace</hi> of thine own <hi>conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> Gods Vice-gerent within thee, and thou maiſt not obey.</p>
               <p>Yet it may be worth thy pains to ſearch again; thou ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt not <hi>ſuffer</hi> upon too
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:160556:76"/> 
                  <hi>ſure</hi> grounds; and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance, <hi>yet,</hi> thou maiſt be in an errour, and God may at length <hi>reveal it to thee.</hi> And that I may offer all my ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, both to thy <hi>conſcience</hi> &amp; the <hi>peace</hi> of the Church, let me beſeech you <hi>thorow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to examine,</hi> &amp; ſatisfy your ſelfe in theſe <hi>four Caſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1 <hi>Wherein</hi> Real <hi>Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition, or the ſhew and</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance <hi>of it lies?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>Whether ſuch things are</hi> ſtill <hi>to be reckoned</hi> Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious, <hi>as have been</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly <hi>uſed to Superſtition?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3 <hi>Whether the</hi> ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cancy <hi>of things impoſed render the things</hi> Superſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious <hi>or ſinful?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="128" facs="tcp:160556:77"/> 4 <hi>Whether it be a</hi> ſinful betraying <hi>the</hi> Chriſtian Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty <hi>to obey the</hi> Law <hi>in things</hi> indifferent <hi>in the Worſhip of God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I know nothing that makes <hi>impoſitions</hi> of this kind ſeem <hi>ſinful</hi> to any, but it may be reduced to theſe <hi>four</hi> heads: give me but a little <hi>liberty to ſpeak my mind briefly</hi> upon <hi>each</hi> of them, and I haſten to a Concluſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="case">
               <pb n="129" facs="tcp:160556:77"/>
               <head>CASE I. <hi>Wherein doth</hi> Superſtition <hi>or the</hi> appearance <hi>of it conſiſt?</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">Reſol.</head>
               <p>THis Caſe hath viſibly two Branches.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1 Touching the <hi>reality,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2 The <hi>appearance</hi> of <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>1 For the <hi>reality</hi> of <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition; all Divines</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that it ſticks not in the <hi>natures</hi> of the things <hi>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed</hi> or <hi>required,</hi> but in the <hi>perſons</hi> that <hi>ſuperſtitiouſly</hi> require or uſe them. <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition</hi> therefore is right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſaid by Divines to be grounded in that <hi>falſe</hi>
                  <pb n="130" facs="tcp:160556:78"/> 
                  <hi>Doctrine</hi> or <hi>ſuperſtitious</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that ſuperſtitious <hi>perſons</hi> have of them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Polanus,</hi> with many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of unqueſtionable <hi>credit</hi> in this particular, hath reduced <hi>thoſe</hi> errours that conſtitute <hi>circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> of Worſhip truly and <hi>really ſuperſtitious,</hi> to <hi>four</hi> heads.</p>
               <p n="1">1 <hi>Meriti:</hi> When wee think God is bound to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward our</hi> inventions, and that by our purſes or la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours therein we <hi>purchaſe</hi> his favour. This is <hi>Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>Cultus Dei:</hi> When things are required as <hi>parts,</hi> or of the eſſence of <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Worſhip,</hi> or ſo uſed. This is <hi>Superſtition.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3 <hi>Perfectionis:</hi> When
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:160556:78"/> we conceive that the true <hi>beauty</hi> and excellency of the Church, and the <hi>perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> of Chriſtianity conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in things of <hi>humane</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention. This is <hi>Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Neceſſitatis:</hi> When ſuch things are required as ſimply <hi>neceſſary</hi> in their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and ſo uſed, when they are but things <hi>indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent.</hi> This is alſo <hi>Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Queſt. <hi>But when may a thing be ſaid to</hi> appear Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious, <hi>or to have the</hi> appearance <hi>of Superſtition; for that alſo muſt be avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> We muſt diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh: There is an <hi>evil ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe,</hi> and an <hi>evil appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance;</hi> and the <hi>firſt</hi> is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:160556:79"/> as well as the <hi>lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi> Many may judg that to be ſuperſtition that is not; their errour doth not <hi>make</hi> it to be ſo <hi>indeed,</hi> or in <hi>appearance;</hi> for then what ſhould eſcape when you have tried it by the meaſure of all men?</p>
                  <p>Therefore we muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that a thing may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear <hi>to me</hi> to be ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, that hath not the <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of ſuperſtition</hi> or evil, properly ſo called.</p>
                  <p>Indeed, when upon evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and undeniable grounds of <hi>general pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice,</hi> it appears to the <hi>ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> and unbiaſſed ſort of Chriſtians, that a thing is <hi>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed</hi> ſuperſtitiouſly, that is, as before, with a <hi>ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious conceit</hi> either of <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:160556:79"/> worſhip, perfection,</hi> or <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity,</hi> then no doubt there is an <hi>appearance</hi> of Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition.</p>
                  <p>But I ſay, grounds of <hi>general</hi> practice; for it is not the ſuperſtitious uſe of ſome <hi>few particular</hi> pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate perſons among <hi>us</hi> (much leſs of <hi>other Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries)</hi> that makes a thing appear ſuperſtitious; the practice muſt be <hi>general with us.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Or rather, would you have an <hi>undoubted</hi> Rule in this Caſe? Look to the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the <hi>Church,</hi> whence the grounds of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition and practice are drawn; if <hi>that,</hi> as I have ſaid, be <hi>falſe</hi> and ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, and it appears that upon thoſe <hi>falſe</hi> and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:160556:80"/> grounds the impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition was raiſed, then there is an <hi>appearance</hi> of evil to be avoided; but if you find <hi>otherwiſe,</hi> you muſt other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe <hi>judge.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If it ſhould be poſſible that <hi>private</hi> Chriſtians have reaſon to reply, We know not the minds of our Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers; for ought we know they may require thoſe things which we ſcruple, upon ſome <hi>ſuperſtitious ground</hi> unknown to us.</p>
                  <p>To this it is eaſie to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. If the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of the Church declars the grounds of ſuch impoſition in <hi>gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral,</hi> that is <hi>viſible,</hi> and that muſt be your rule in judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the grounds of <hi>particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar</hi> things impoſed, till the
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:160556:80"/> 
                     <hi>contrary</hi> is declared, or till you have ſome unqueſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable reaſon to <hi>ſuſpect</hi> the deſigns of your <hi>Governors</hi> to betray the Church to <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition</hi> and Idolatry, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the known <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine</hi> of it.</p>
                  <p>In the mean while, if nothing ſavouring of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition aforeſaid be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared in the impoſition, as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, <hi>Quod ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Epiſt. 118. ad <hi>Januar.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>contra fidem,</hi> &amp;c: That which is neither againſt faith or holineſs ought to be held <hi>indifferent;</hi> and for the <hi>ſociety</hi> of thoſe among whom we live, to be <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed</hi> unto.</p>
                  <p>Suppoſe you do not know the minds of your Rulers, yet you owe them <hi>charity</hi> as well as <hi>obedience,</hi>
                     <pb n="136" facs="tcp:160556:81"/> and <hi>that</hi> thinks no harm, but welcoms every thing, eſpecially from Superiours, with the beſt <hi>interpretation.</hi> 
                     <q>There are (ſaith <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine,</hi> full to our purpoſe) <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Aug.</hi> l. 2. de Serm. in Mont.</note> certain middle or indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent actions, which we are ignorant with what mind they are done (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they may be done either with a good or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil intent); <hi>de quibus te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merarium eſt judicare, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xime ut condemnemus;</hi> which things it is a raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to <hi>judge,</hi> much more to <hi>condemn.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="case">
               <pb n="137" facs="tcp:160556:81"/>
               <head>CASE II. <hi>Whether ſuch things as</hi> have been <hi>uſed ſuperſtitiouſly muſt be reckoned Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious</hi> ſtill.</head>
               <head type="sub">Reſol.</head>
               <p>THis doubt is alſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved upon the <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi> grounds. For,</p>
               <p n="1">1 If <hi>Superſtition</hi> conſiſts not in the <hi>nature</hi> of the thing, but in the <hi>ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous conceit</hi> and <hi>uſe</hi> of it, then <hi>ſuperſtition</hi> cleaves <hi>no long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> to any thing, when the thing is <hi>purged</hi> and freed from the ſuperſtitious <hi>do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and uſe,</hi> opinion and practice aforeſaid.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="138" facs="tcp:160556:82"/> 2 None can reaſonably doubt but that upon <hi>this</hi> ground <hi>Superſtition</hi> is <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable</hi> from a thing that hath been thus abuſed; as one ſaies well, <hi>Nothing can be ſo far gone into the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils power, but may be redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to Gods Glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Therefore, as hath been ſaid, we muſt ſtill have recourſe to the <hi>reaſon</hi> of the <hi>uſage</hi> at preſent, and the preſent <hi>grounds</hi> of the <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition;</hi> would you judge righteous in this weighty particular.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Superſtition</hi> is reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>two</hi> waies; either by <hi>aboliſhing</hi> the thing, or <hi>removing</hi> the <hi>abuſe:</hi> Now which is the <hi>beſt</hi> and moſt effectual courſe to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, muſt be left to the
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:160556:82"/> 
                  <hi>wiſedom</hi> and zeal of <hi>Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours;</hi> yet <hi>Reaſon</hi> judges ſo far, <hi>Fruſtra fit per plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra, &amp;c.</hi> If the end can be attained without more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do, <hi>i. e.</hi> if by <hi>inſtruction</hi> and <hi>injunctions</hi> the thing may be <hi>reduced</hi> to a lawful and laudable uſe, what need of the abolition of it?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ad eundem finem multis mediis pervenitur;</hi> We may arrive at the <hi>ſame</hi> end by <hi>divers</hi> means; the <hi>means</hi> are of no moment, as ſuch, further then they advance the <hi>end.</hi> If ſuperſtition be <hi>removed,</hi> no great matter <hi>which way,</hi> as appeareth in the practice of good <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekias;</hi> he took away the <hi>High places,</hi> brake the <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages,</hi> cut down the <hi>Groves,</hi> brake the <hi>Brazen Serpent;</hi>
                  <pb n="140" facs="tcp:160556:83"/> thus he endeavoured with all pious zeal to <hi>reform</hi> by the firſt courſe, the <hi>aboliti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of the things abuſed; yet he <hi>ſpared</hi> the Chappel which <hi>Solomon</hi> built for <hi>Aſhtoreth</hi> the Idol of <hi>the Sydonians,</hi> and for the <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſh</hi> the Idol of the <hi>Moa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bites,</hi> and for <hi>Milcom</hi> the abomination of the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Ammon,</hi> in hopes, no doubt, to ſever the <hi>Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry</hi> from the <hi>Places,</hi> and by a <hi>milder</hi> courſe of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, <note place="margin">Vid. <hi>Greg.</hi> l. 10. Ep. 71.</note> to reduce theſe by his wiſedom to the uſe and ſervice of the <hi>true God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yet upon ſuppoſition that the <hi>Idolatry</hi> or ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition <hi>cannot be ſevered</hi> from the uſe of the thing, or very hardly done, <hi>Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry and ſuperſtition</hi> muſt
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:160556:83"/> have no indulgence; the <hi>Serpent</hi> it ſelf in ſuch a caſe muſt be <hi>broken in pieces.</hi> Here that famous Rule of Pope <hi>Stephen</hi> is appproved by all; <hi>Per hoc, Magna Authoritas,</hi> &amp;c. <q>For this cauſe that Authority is eſteemed great in the Church, that if ſome of our Predeceſſors have done ſome things which at that time might be without fault, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards are turned into er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour and ſuperſtition, without any delay, and with great authority, they may be deſtroyed by Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Yet to this rule we muſt <hi>oppoſe</hi> that excellent obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ad publi. Col.</hi> 154.</note> of St <hi>Auguſtine, Cum Templa, Idola, Luci,</hi>
                  <pb n="142" facs="tcp:160556:84"/> 
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 
                  <q>When Temples, I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols, Groves, or any thing of like qualily, by lawful Authority are ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inated, if they be tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated into <hi>common</hi> (not <hi>proper)</hi> uſes, and conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the <hi>honour</hi> of the true <hi>God,</hi> that falleth out in them which happeneth alſo in men, when as of <hi>ſacriledgious</hi> and ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, they are <hi>converted</hi> to the true Religion.—So <hi>God</hi> (ſaith he) comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that the <hi>Wood</hi> which grew in the Groves of ſtrange gods ſhould be u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the <hi>Holocauſt;</hi> and that all the <hi>gold and ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver</hi> of <hi>Jericho</hi> ſhould be brought into the <hi>Lords Treaſury.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>De <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> Veſt. ad Nop.</note>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Becauſe (as the Learned
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:160556:84"/> 
                     <hi>Bucer</hi> teacheth) to be a legal or <hi>Antichriſtian Rite,</hi> ſticks in <hi>no creature</hi> of God, in no Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in no Figure, in no colour; or in any work of God, but in the <hi>mind</hi> and profeſſion of thoſe that abuſe the good crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of God, <hi>ad impias ſignificationes,</hi> to wicked or ungodly purpoſes.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Hereupon, <hi>Scio</hi> (inquit <hi>Beza) nonnullos ſublata cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis Adoratione, aliquem ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni crucis uſum retinniſſe; utuntur igitur ipſi, ſicut par eſt, ſuâ libertate.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But laſtly, Admit that our Rulers ought to <hi>aboliſh</hi> the thing that hath been ſo uſed to <hi>ſuperſtition,</hi> but do not think fit to do it; &amp; <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn</hi> us by their commands
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:160556:85"/> to leave the ſuperſtitious uſe, and to uſe it as we <hi>lawfully</hi> may; it need not enter into a Queſtion, Whether we ought not to forſake the <hi>ſuperſtition,</hi> and alſo to obey Authority in the lawful uſe of that thing without fear of ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="case">
               <head>CASE III. <hi>Whether the imputing of</hi> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificancy <hi>to things impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed render them</hi> Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious?</head>
               <head type="sub">Reſol.</head>
               <p>TRuly ſome Reverend and Learned men ſeem ſo affrighted at the
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:160556:85"/> very mention of <hi>ſacred myſtical Ceremonies, ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant ſymbolical Rites</hi> of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Inſtitution, that I cannot but fear, rhat they have apprehended ſome ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great danger in them.</p>
               <p>Should we once grant, that Ceremonies of humane Inſtitution might be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to ſignifie <hi>the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of God,</hi> or the <hi>grace</hi> of the <hi>Sacraments;</hi> or to be a <hi>means</hi> of receiving any bleſſing from God; no doubt, there is ſo much <hi>dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi> in it, that if corrupt and ſuperſtitious men ſhould at any time rule the Church, we may quickly have not onely <hi>Seven</hi> but Seventy times ſeven, if not <hi>intire,</hi> yet, <hi>Semi-Sacraments;</hi> the Church and ſervice of God
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:160556:86"/> being thereby obnoxious to all the antick and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceited crotchers that the vain imaginations of over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curious men can cumber them with, untill they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſtench in the noſtrils of all <hi>ſober</hi> and ſtaid <hi>men,</hi> and of <hi>God</hi> himſelf with the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But, if by <hi>Rites</hi> and Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies we mean onely the <hi>Circumſtances</hi> of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Worſhip; by Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture left to the <hi>liberty</hi> and prudence of the Church: and by the <hi>ſignificancy</hi> of them, we intend nothing, but that they are fitted to commend the <hi>exerciſe,</hi> with <hi>order</hi> and decency, to expreſs the <hi>gravity</hi> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion of the <hi>Worſhippers;</hi> tending alſo (as ſuch things
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:160556:86"/> are capable) to unity and <hi>edification:</hi> if this be all, truly I cannot diſcover <hi>ſo much</hi> danger.</p>
               <p>Yea, give me leave to add, that to quarrel with them, becauſe they are <hi>ſuch,</hi> ſeems to be angry with <hi>theſe</hi> Ceremonies which are <hi>better,</hi> and <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe</hi> they are better then others; and to quarrel with their <hi>very fitneſs,</hi> and their conformity to the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral <hi>Rules of Scripture,</hi> by which alone they ought to be meaſured.</p>
               <p>Again, if nothing that is ſo <hi>purely Indifferent,</hi> as to be of <hi>no uſe</hi> or ſervice; and not to be more expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient then inexpedient, ought to be impoſed, as all moderate men allow; and,
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:160556:87"/> according to the opinion in hand, Nothing that hath <hi>its uſe</hi> or ſignificancy may be required: who ſees not but the Church is <hi>crucified</hi> between <hi>two Opinions,</hi> that openly <hi>rob</hi> her of <hi>all power</hi> about things indifferent.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Some</hi> very wiſe and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuſpected perſons have freely declared themſelves not to diſcover any <hi>ſuch danger</hi> in the <hi>bare ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cancy</hi> of the Rites of the Church, as others are af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frighted with. <q>It is not lawfull (ſaith <hi>Peter Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr</hi> to <hi>Hooper)</hi> to deprive the Church of that <hi>liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> that ſhe ſhould not by her actions and <hi>Rites</hi> of the Church, <hi>aliquid ſignificare, ſignify</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. Yea, (further ſaith</q>
                  <pb n="149" facs="tcp:160556:87"/> he) the very <hi>Apoſtle</hi> himſelf uſed <hi>that</hi> liberty, when he taught, <hi>ut illis ſignis,</hi> that with thoſe ſignes they ſhould be <hi>admoniſhed</hi> of their duty. Again, <hi>Rerum ſignificationes, &amp;c.</hi> the ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifications of things call to our minds, <hi>quid nos deceat,</hi> what is expedient. <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtri magis memores ſint ſui officii.</hi> [Vid. <hi>Aret. in</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 10. &amp; 16. 16. <hi>Pet. Mart.</hi> in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16. 26. <hi>Geneva Annotations</hi> in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16. 20. <hi>Perkins Caſe. Conſci.</hi> cap. 3. Sect. 3.]</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Calvin</hi> alſo is nothing <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Calv.</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtit. lib. 4. c. 10. 28, 29.</note> fearful to de iver his minde in the point: There are (ſaith he) <hi>Rites which draw Veneration to holy things,</hi> &amp;c. with ſuch <hi>little helps</hi> we are provoked to piety.—
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:160556:88"/> They are <hi>adapted</hi> to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence of holy Myſteries; thereby the exerciſe is <hi>ſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> to holin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſs.—They are not <hi>without fruit.—</hi>Thereby the faithfull are <hi>admoniſhed</hi> with what mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty and religion they are to worſhip God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Kneeling</hi> (ſaith <hi>Beza) when we receive the Signes, hath a ſhew of Godly and Chriſtian Veneration.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="case">
               <pb n="151" facs="tcp:160556:88"/>
               <head>CASE IV. <hi>Whether it be a</hi> ſinfull be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traying <hi>our</hi> Chriſtian li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty <hi>to</hi> obey <hi>the</hi> Law <hi>in things Indifferent in the Worſhip of God.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">Reſol.</head>
               <p>THis Queſtion ſeems to engage <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar;</hi> and to cauſe a quarrel betwixt <hi>Duty</hi> and <hi>Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> which neither <hi>God</hi> or <hi>Ceſar, Duty</hi> or <hi>Liber<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y</hi> will own or defend.</p>
               <p>The doubt apparently reſults out of a too groſs miſtake of the <hi>nature</hi> of true <hi>Gospel-Liberty;</hi> the Internal part whereof,
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:160556:89"/> though it indeed <hi>free</hi> us from <hi>Inward</hi> Bondage, yet <hi>binds</hi> us the faſter in Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice <hi>to God:</hi> ſo the <hi>exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal</hi> part thereof doth alſo deliver us from <hi>outward</hi> ſlavery to the luſts of <hi>men;</hi> yet it the <hi>more</hi> obligeth us in <hi>duty</hi> to Superiors.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Polanus</hi> placeth Exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Chriſtian Liberty (w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> indeed is properly <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> as it may be diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from <hi>Goſpel-</hi>Liberty) in two things. A Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty from the <hi>Law of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes;</hi> 2. A Liberty in the uſe of <hi>Indifferent</hi> things. Now, though the <hi>firſt</hi> branch may not be touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, yet, he doubts not in the leaſt, but that the <hi>latter</hi> may be determined, upon juſt occaſion of the <hi>Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:160556:89"/> order,</hi> by lawfull Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Libertas Chriſtiana eſt duplex; à Legibus</hi> Moſis, <hi>&amp; in Adiaphoris, quales ſunt Ceremoniae humanâ au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toritate inſtitutae, boni ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis cauſâ.</hi> Chriſtian liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty (ſaith <hi>Polanus)</hi> is two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold; from the Laws of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> and in things <hi>indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent:</hi> of which ſort (mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning things Indifferent) are Ceremonies appointed by humane Authority for orders ſake.</p>
               <p>Now neither of theſe branches of Chriſtian Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty can be ſoberly thought to make void the Law, as Moral or Natural, in any one jot or tittle of it, which our Saviour came to fulfill, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. and
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:160556:90"/> eſtabliſh, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. <hi>ult.</hi> but to aſſert, that <hi>Rulers</hi> have no power in things <hi>Indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent,</hi> becauſe of <hi>Chriſtian liberty,</hi> ſeems to weaken he arm of Authority Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical, Civil, Political, Oeconomical, and even to raze out the <hi>fifth Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement</hi> of the Moral Law; yea, what <hi>unnatural</hi> conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences of all diſorder are like to enſue, in <hi>Church,</hi> in <hi>State,</hi> in <hi>Families,</hi> and all <hi>Societies</hi> in the world? the beauty and comlineſs of all which lies not a litle in the due order of things Indifferent.</p>
               <p>Yea, how often is the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> himſelf the great Aſſert of Chriſtian Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie, thus made an <hi>Inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> of it? how Injuriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:160556:90"/> did that famous <hi>Synod,</hi> Act. 15. <hi>binde</hi> the Church to thoſe indifferent things? What <hi>Council, Father, Scholman, Church,</hi> nay, what <hi>wiſe man</hi> was ever of this opinion? or who is that <hi>ſolid Writer,</hi> in any age almoſt, that hath not declared the <hi>contrary?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Give me leave, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, to repeat it, the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of <hi>Chriſtian Liberty</hi> is much miſtaken: It is not only <hi>conſiſtent</hi> with, but it even <hi>conſiſteth</hi> in the determination of things in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different by lawful Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. It is <hi>one part</hi> of this liberty (as <hi>Calvin</hi> aſſerts) <note place="margin">Libertas aufertur, ablato Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re &amp; Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gibus.</note> that the Church hath pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to <hi>regulate</hi> the <hi>Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantes</hi> of Worſhip, for peace and unity, order and
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:160556:91"/> decency; and it is, no doubt, another great part of the ſaid Liberty, that the members of the ſame may, without ſin, <hi>obey</hi> their <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers</hi> in ſuch determinations.</p>
               <p>It is moſt worthily ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> that is a part of our <hi>Freedom,</hi> as Chriſtians, that we may be the <hi>Lords free-men</hi> in our <note place="margin">1 Cor. 7. 20, 22.</note> 
                  <hi>publick</hi> capacity, and yet <hi>ſervants</hi> in our <hi>private;</hi> our Chriſtian liberty being not infringed by our outward duty.</p>
               <p>Moreover, that for the good of <hi>Society,</hi> the <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation</hi> of our ſelves from <hi>legal penalties,</hi> for our <hi>maintenance</hi> and liveli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, we may be ſubject to the commands and laws of men, I take to be a
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:160556:91"/> very <hi>valuable part</hi> of our li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty alſo; provided no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing be required or acted againſt the <hi>Supremacy</hi> of our Lord <hi>Paramount</hi> in Heaven.</p>
               <p>But let us a little more <note place="margin">1 Cor. 7. 20, 21, 23.</note> diſtinctly conſider the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, <hi>Let every one abide in the ſame calling</hi> (private) <hi>wherin he is called;</hi> that is, to be a Chriſtian: <hi>Art thou called a ſervant,</hi> &amp;c. Whence briefly note,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Are not all that are <hi>called</hi> to be Chriſtians, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to the <hi>liberty</hi> of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians?</p>
               <p n="2">2. Doth not the <hi>Text</hi> aſſure us, that <hi>this</hi> liberty to <hi>which</hi> we are <hi>called</hi> is truly conſiſtent with the <hi>Condition</hi> in <hi>which</hi> we are called? otherwiſe why
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:160556:92"/> ſhould we <hi>abide</hi> in it?</p>
               <p n="3">3. Is not the ſtate of all perſons, <hi>called</hi> to be Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, (except <hi>ſupream</hi> Magiſtrates) a ſtate of <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection</hi> and ſervitude?</p>
               <p n="4">4. Doth it not then moſt cleerly follow, that Chriſtian liberty <hi>conſiſteth</hi> with, and <hi>obligeth</hi> unto <hi>all, kind</hi> of <hi>duty</hi> to all kind of Governours, to <hi>Fathers, Maſters, Husbands,</hi> (as the very <hi>Quakers</hi> acknowledg) <hi>Paſtours, Kings,</hi> and to <hi>God</hi> himſelf (as all good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians have cauſe to glory) and that upon the firmeſt bonds and ties imaginable, of <hi>Wrath,</hi> of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and the <hi>Lords ſake.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nam etſi conſcientias proprie ſolus Deus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <pb n="159" facs="tcp:160556:92"/>
               <p>
                  <q>For (ſaith <hi>Beza)</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Bez.</hi> ep. 20.</note> 
                     <hi>God</hi> alone can properly bind the <hi>conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence;</hi> yet ſo fat as the <hi>Church,</hi> with reſpect to <hi>Order</hi> and <hi>Decency,</hi> and thereby to <hi>Edification,</hi> doth rightly enjoyn, or make <hi>Laws</hi> concerning things <hi>Indifferent,</hi> thoſe ſame Laws are to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by all pious Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; and they do ſo far <hi>bind the conſcience</hi> as that no man <hi>[Sciens &amp; pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens &amp; rebellandi animo]</hi> wittingly and willingly with a purpoſe to diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey, can either do what is ſo forbidden, or omit what is ſo commanded, <hi>abſque peccato,</hi> without ſin.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="case">
               <pb n="160" facs="tcp:160556:93"/>
               <head>CASE III. <hi>What are we to do in caſe ſuch things are comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded us, as though</hi> we <hi>judg them</hi> lawful, <hi>yet</hi> others <hi>judge them</hi> ſinful, <hi>and will be</hi> offended <hi>at our doing of them?</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">Reſol.</head>
               <p>VVE have already conſidered what is to be done, if things <hi>ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in themſelves,</hi> or judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo <hi>by us,</hi> be injoyned: We are arrived to the <hi>ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate</hi> ſcruple, touching the <hi>offence</hi> that <hi>others</hi> may be likely to take at our pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, who conceive thoſe things which are <hi>injoyned</hi>
                  <pb n="161" facs="tcp:160556:93"/> to be <hi>unlawful,</hi> and that we ſhall <hi>ſin</hi> if we do them. And the Queſtion is, <hi>What is to be done in</hi> this Caſe?</p>
               <p>The ſcruple is evident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly grounded in the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> Directions about <hi>ſcandal;</hi> the ſum of which is, that we muſt not uſe our liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in indifferent things to the <hi>offence of our weak</hi> bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>For <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> to this great and preſent doubt, we muſt have <hi>liberty</hi> a little to <hi>diſtinguiſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>1. We muſt diſtinguiſh of the <hi>object</hi> of <hi>ſcandal;</hi> it may be ſuch as offends only <hi>one way;</hi> and it may be ſuch as offends both <hi>ways;</hi> that is, firſt the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a thing may offend ſome, when the <hi>not doing</hi>
                  <pb n="162" facs="tcp:160556:94"/> of it offends none: This was the Caſe in the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles</hi> time; the taking of <hi>meat</hi> offered to <hi>Idols</hi> was apt to offend the <hi>weak</hi> bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren; but the <hi>not eating</hi> of ſuch meat was not like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to offend any body: In ſuch a Caſe 'tis evident, we ought not to eat to the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of our brother.</p>
               <p>But in <hi>ſome Caſes</hi> there is a <hi>neceſſity of offence,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we <hi>do</hi> the thing, or whether we do it not; as in caſe of <hi>Conformity,</hi> our very caſe, ſome, you ſay, that are weak will be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended if we <hi>do</hi> conform; and you cannot ſay but that <hi>ſome</hi> whom you judg <hi>weak</hi> alſo, will be offended if we <hi>do not.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now in this caſe there
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:160556:94"/> is no <hi>remedy,</hi> ſeeing I muſt do one or other, <hi>conform,</hi> or <hi>not;</hi> but to fly to that excellent Rule of <hi>Polanus,</hi> and to conſider the <hi>perſons offended</hi> on <hi>both</hi> ſides, and to weigh the <hi>nature</hi> of the <hi>offence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hereupon we muſt reſt ſatisfied in <hi>this</hi> iſſue; where <hi>moſt,</hi> and of <hi>moſt conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> are offended; and where the nature of the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence is <hi>moſt haynous,</hi> there we muſt forbear to uſe our liberty, and either do or not do the thing in queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and ſo on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</p>
               <p>Let us then apply, and faithfully anſwer our ſelves whether the doing a lawful thing enjoyned by Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, that will offend our
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:160556:95"/> weak brethren be likely to offend <hi>more perſons</hi> and perſons of <hi>more conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and give offence of a <hi>more heinous</hi> nature, than the <hi>not doing</hi> of that law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full thing againſt the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of Authority.</p>
               <p>Here ſeem to be three branches of the Compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: 1. Where <hi>more</hi> are likely to be offended. 2. Where more <hi>conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable</hi> perſons. 3. Where the nature of the <hi>offence</hi> is <hi>fouleſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Truly, I ſoberly think, that <hi>Conformity</hi> in ſuch lawfull things need not fear to compare with <hi>Non con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity,</hi> in <hi>any</hi> one of theſe <hi>three.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. If the Queſtion be, Whether Conformity or
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:160556:95"/> Non-conformity be likely to offend <hi>moſt</hi> individual perſons in the Nation, it will not be difficult to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer. Its poſſible, the <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing</hi> of ſuch things <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> offend many <hi>more</hi> then t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>not practiſing;</hi> but when things are once <hi>impoſed,</hi> ſo <hi>wiſe a Nation</hi> will, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, leave little room for the compariſon betwixt the <hi>extent</hi> of ſcandal by <hi>Obedience</hi> and by <hi>Diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. And much more, if the Queſtion be touching the <hi>conſiderableneſs</hi> of the <hi>perſons</hi> offended on <hi>both ſides.</hi> 'Tis too true, that <hi>Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience</hi> in ſuch a caſe is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſtirr up <hi>trouble,</hi> envy, diſcontent &amp; murmuring in the mindes of many of the
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:160556:96"/> 
                  <hi>ordinary</hi> ſort of people; but whether, as to the great ends of the <hi>peace</hi> and good of the <hi>Church,</hi> the <hi>ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> ſort be the more <hi>conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>able,</hi> will hardly brook <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> inquiry. Whereas, our <hi>Diſobedience,</hi> beſides the offence of <hi>ordinary</hi> peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, is too likely to offend the <hi>King,</hi> the <hi>Court,</hi> the <hi>Councell,</hi> the <hi>Parliament,</hi> the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> the <hi>Lawyers,</hi> the <hi>Nobility,</hi> the <hi>Gentry,</hi> or beyond controverſie the <hi>greater part</hi> of them <hi>all;</hi> but even thus farr the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument is invincible <hi>(à Minore ad Majus)</hi>: If we muſt forbear our liberty in caſe of offence to our <hi>weak brother,</hi> much more in caſe of offence to <hi>Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="167" facs="tcp:160556:96"/> 3. Eſpecially, if we conſider the <hi>nature</hi> of the <hi>offence</hi> alſo on both ſides. Where, firſt, we may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare the offence on <hi>both ſides</hi> with the offence the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> mentions, and then <hi>weigh</hi> them <hi>one</hi> againſt <hi>ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Firſt, <hi>comparing</hi> the <hi>ſcandal</hi> likely to happen upon our <hi>obedience,</hi> with the ſcandal of the <hi>weak</hi> mentioned by the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> there ſeems to be this great <hi>difference:</hi> the ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal mentioned by the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle,</hi> was, <hi>chiefly,</hi> if not (as an <hi>eminent</hi> perſon aſſerts) <hi>onely, unto ſin.</hi> And the great reaſon the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> gives, why we muſt not uſe our <hi>liberty</hi> to the <hi>offence</hi> of our <hi>weak</hi> brother, is, leſt
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:160556:97"/> we lay a <hi>ſtumbling-block</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 14. 13, 15, 20, 21. 1 Cor. 8. 9, 10, 11, 12, 13.</note> before him, whereat he may <hi>fall:</hi> that is, leaſt he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume after our <hi>example,</hi> to do ſomething againſt his Conſcience, and ſo ſin <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Chriſt,</hi> and be likely to <hi>periſh</hi> or to be <hi>deſtroyed;</hi> the <hi>danger,</hi> therefore the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> tells us, lies not ſo much in <hi>offending</hi> our bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſenſe, as in one <hi>making</hi> him by our evil example to <hi>offend.</hi> Wherefore, the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> concludes, <hi>If meat make my brother to offend, I will eat no fleſh, &amp;c.</hi> 1 Cor. 8. 13.</p>
               <p>But now the <hi>offence</hi> that is moſt likely to enſue up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our <hi>conformity,</hi> is quite of <hi>another</hi> nature, there is litle fear of drawing our
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:160556:97"/> 
                  <hi>offended</hi> brethren to <hi>like</hi> the waies of <hi>Conformity</hi> by the practice of Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts; but rather they will like <hi>Conformity</hi> and the perſons <hi>conforming</hi> ſo much the worſe, and grow the more <hi>bitter</hi> againſt them.</p>
               <p>The <hi>reaſon</hi> of this diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, I conceive, lies thus; In the time of the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> thoſe were genera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked upon as the <hi>ſtrongeſt</hi> diſciples that <hi>knew</hi> their <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty</hi> beſt; and the others, that were <hi>weak,</hi> were apt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt to be <hi>offended;</hi> but now, thoſe that pretend <hi>offence</hi> are the <hi>ſtrongeſt</hi> in their own opinion; and they judge it a <hi>weakneſs</hi> in thoſe that do conform: and no doubt, if any be likely
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:160556:98"/> to follow our <hi>examples</hi> in <hi>conformity,</hi> out of an opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of our <hi>ability</hi> to judg <hi>better</hi> then <hi>themſelves;</hi> they will as eaſily follow our <hi>Judgment</hi> too, if we firſt uſe due means of <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction</hi> to them; and then all the <hi>ſcruple</hi> is va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed and gone.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Secondly, let us weigh them <hi>one</hi> againſt <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother;</hi> and compare the <hi>offence</hi> received by our <hi>weak</hi> brethren upon our <hi>obedience,</hi> with that recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by <hi>Authority</hi> upon our <hi>diſobedience.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If we onely do that which we may lawfully do, and which we are <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded</hi> to do, we do not <hi>give</hi> our <hi>weak</hi> brother any offence, though he <hi>take</hi> it:
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:160556:98"/> there is not that <hi>per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe,</hi> or naturally flowing out of the uſe of my <hi>liberty,</hi> or the doing of my <hi>duty,</hi> that would <hi>hurt</hi> my brother, or <hi>tempt</hi> him to <hi>ſin;</hi> he takes occaſion of himſelf, not at all given by me.</p>
               <p>But now, by <hi>diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> (if the thing be <hi>law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</hi> that is injoined) we <hi>give</hi> offence to Authority, <hi>directly</hi> and properly ſo; and, as we have ſhewed, we can hardly eſcape <hi>ſin</hi> herein againſt the <hi>fifth Commandement;</hi> which, in every <hi>iota,</hi> as well as all the reſt, our very liberty it ſelf eſtabliſheth.</p>
               <p>The <hi>ſum</hi> is this; by refuſing to conform in ſuch a <hi>lawfull</hi> caſe, leſt we ſhould <hi>offend</hi> our weak
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:160556:99"/> brother, ſeems <hi>directly</hi> to <hi>ſin</hi> our ſelves, to avoid an <hi>occaſion</hi> of <hi>ſin</hi> to him; to offend <hi>God,</hi> the <hi>King,</hi> the <hi>Law,</hi> the <hi>Church,</hi> and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> too, by <hi>not doing</hi> our duty, leſt we ſhould offend our brother by <hi>doing</hi> it.</p>
               <p>Therefore, we muſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh betwixt things <hi>Indifferent,</hi> that are <hi>not</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the actual <hi>command</hi> of Authority; and ſuch as <hi>are,</hi> before they are <hi>comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,</hi> things <hi>Indifferent,</hi> are in our <hi>liberty:</hi> and then, the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> Rule holds, we muſt <hi>not uſe</hi> our <hi>liberty</hi> to the <hi>offence</hi> of our brethren; but what is required by <hi>Authority,</hi> if it be no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in our <hi>liberty,</hi> we muſt minde our <hi>duty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>This</hi> Rule therefore
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:160556:99"/> greatly concerns <hi>Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates</hi> in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ir Impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, who ought ſtill to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the weighty advice of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Calvin:</hi> Let <hi>Charity</hi> ſubmit to <hi>Faith,</hi> and <hi>Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to Charity;</hi> but <hi>Subjects</hi> muſt not <hi>ſin,</hi> that they may <hi>pleaſe</hi> their <hi>Prince,</hi> much leſs their <hi>brother.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Beſides, we may diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh of <hi>offence,</hi> with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to our <hi>brother offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded;</hi> if we offend him by <hi>doing our duty,</hi> we one<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y <hi>tempt</hi> him to do <hi>his</hi> duty, though againſt his <hi>conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence;</hi> on the other ſide, if we <hi>omit our duty,</hi> leſt we offend our <hi>brother,</hi> do not we offend him <hi>more</hi> in the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> ſence, by tempting him to <hi>continue in ſin,</hi> and
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:160556:100"/> to embolden himſelf in ſin with a <hi>worſe conſcience?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="case">
               <head>CASE. <hi>The Apoſtle hath laid down a</hi> Rule, <hi>how we are to uſe our liberty in things In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different, towards our weak brother: can</hi> Man <hi>by his commands</hi> alter this Rule, <hi>or take off the</hi> force <hi>of it?</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">Reſol.</head>
               <p>THe <hi>Apoſtles Rule</hi> is abſolutely unaltera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, where the <hi>reaſon</hi> of it holds; and the <hi>object</hi> is the ſame that is where the matter is <hi>ſtill indifferent.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="175" facs="tcp:160556:100"/>
               <p> 2. Man cannot make things <hi>Indifferent</hi> to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come <hi>neceſſary</hi> in their <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture;</hi> yet lawful Authority may and ought to <hi>judge</hi> when the <hi>exigencies</hi> of the Church make any thing neceſſary, as to its <hi>preſent uſe,</hi> or forbearance. <hi>Theſe neceſsary things</hi> (ſaith that <hi>Councel,</hi> Act. 15.) though <note place="margin">v. 28.</note> they were not <hi>all</hi> neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in their <hi>nature,</hi> yet the <hi>Councel</hi> judged them ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary as to the <hi>preſent good</hi> of the Church.</p>
               <p>3. In ſuch Caſes, for the publick good of the Church, <hi>Governours</hi> may and ought to determine the uſe of <hi>Indifferent</hi> things by their <hi>prudent</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions; <hi>It ſeemed good to the Holy Ghoſt and to us</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">28.</note>
                  <pb n="176" facs="tcp:160556:101"/> 
                  <hi>to lay upon you no other bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then then theſe neceſſary things.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And no leſs remarkably we finde St <hi>Pauls</hi> power put forth, in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. and o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>her places, in determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>many Indifferent</hi> things, for <hi>order</hi> and <hi>decen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy</hi> in the Church of God.</p>
               <p>4. But what doth all this <hi>ſignifie,</hi> if theſe <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolical</hi> Injunctions have no force, when a <hi>diſconten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> perſon ſhall ſay he is <hi>offended?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Put caſe that after the <hi>decree</hi> of the Synod in <hi>Act.</hi> 15. a particular <hi>mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> ſhould have been <hi>of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended,</hi> that his brother refuſed to eat meat of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to <hi>Idols,</hi> pleading that it was <hi>ſuperſtition</hi> in
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:160556:101"/> him, or a loſing or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traying the <hi>Chriſtian Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty:</hi> Or that others had been <hi>offended</hi> at thoſe particulars of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency</hi> and Order injoined by the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> to the Church of <hi>Corinth;</hi> ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging that they were <hi>not</hi> commanded of the <hi>Lord,</hi> that therefore they were <hi>Humane Inventions, New Ordinances, Additions</hi> to Gods Word, and <hi>Will-Worſhip.</hi> Can any ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, that the <hi>reſt</hi> of the people had been diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged of their <hi>duty,</hi> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to that famous <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod,</hi> or that excellent Governour the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> or that they were bound to ſuſpend their
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:160556:102"/> 
                  <hi>Obedience,</hi> leſt they ſhould <hi>offend</hi> ſuch <hi>ſcrapulous</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons? I cannot think it.</p>
               <p>We muſt not oppoſe <hi>Liberty</hi> to <hi>Neceſſity; Charity</hi> to <hi>Duty;</hi> or the <hi>Offence</hi> of the <hi>Weak,</hi> to the <hi>Higher Powers.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="case">
               <pb n="179" facs="tcp:160556:102"/>
               <head>CASE I. <hi>But it is vehemently urged by my brethren in the<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, <hi>that even their</hi> credit <hi>and reputation will not ſuffer them to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form; they ſhall thus be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come</hi> vile <hi>to the</hi> people, <hi>as men that will do any thing to ſave their</hi> Live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; <hi>and then their</hi> Miniſtry <hi>will be</hi> fruitleſs, <hi>and do no good among them; What is to be done in ſuch a Caſe?</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">Reſol.</head>
               <p n="1">1. THis Caſe ſeems to ariſe from <hi>pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> and not <hi>conſcience:</hi> Herein we not pretend to
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:160556:103"/> fly from <hi>ſin</hi> to <hi>ſuffering,</hi> but from <hi>one ſort</hi> of ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering to <hi>another,</hi> that is judged rather to be cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen; from ſuffering in our <hi>Reputation</hi> by <hi>Conformity,</hi> to the <hi>Penalties</hi> of the Law for <hi>diſobedience;</hi> which, when all things are conſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, will be found to ſavour more of the ſtout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and <hi>Magnanimity</hi> of an <hi>Heathen,</hi> then of the <hi>meekneſs,</hi> humility, and ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denial of a Chriſtian, or a <hi>Miniſter</hi> of Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="2">2. A <hi>good name</hi> indeed is a very pretious thing; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd to <hi>blot</hi> and ſtain it with any thing that is <hi>ſinful</hi> is to be abhorred more then death; for <hi>a good name is better then life;</hi> but to ſuffer therein <hi>without a cauſe,</hi> or
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:160556:103"/> in a <hi>good cauſe;</hi> to ſuffer therein for <hi>well doing,</hi> as the <hi>Apoſtle ſpeaks,</hi> the more precious it is, the more <hi>thank-worthy</hi> are ſuch ſufferings, &amp; the more like <hi>Martyrdom.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. But if the <hi>things</hi> be lawful that are required, &amp; the Authority be lawful that requires them, and God commandeth you <hi>to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey them that rule over you,</hi> in things that are lawful; if the publique <hi>Peace,</hi> the good of <hi>ſouls,</hi> the ſafety of the <hi>Church,</hi> as well as your own <hi>proſperity,</hi> do truly depend upon your <hi>confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity;</hi> and upon theſe, or like reſpects of <hi>Peaaee, Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> and <hi>ſafety,</hi> you do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form, and are therefore <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached</hi> and wounded in
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:160556:104"/> your <hi>Names,</hi> I ſee not but that you ſuffer in a very good cauſe, and your <hi>Names</hi> are <hi>Martyrs</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and the <hi>ſouls</hi> of the people; in ſuch a caſe doubt not to <hi>commit your ſouls</hi> and <hi>names</hi> into the hands of your <hi>God</hi> in <hi>well-doing,</hi> as into the hands of a <hi>faithful Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor,</hi> who will find a time and a way to <hi>wipe</hi> off the <hi>dirt</hi> from his <hi>Jewels,</hi> and make <hi>your Righteouſneſs ſhine as the light, and your innocency as the noon-day: When all men ſpeak evil of you</hi> (ſuch a time there may be) for Chriſts ſake, <hi>rejoyce</hi> and be exceeding glad, for great is your reward in <hi>hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. But let us take a
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:160556:104"/> more ſteady view of the <hi>danger</hi> which your <hi>reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> is really in, by <hi>confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity</hi> in lawful things. In order thereunto let us <hi>weigh</hi> the ſtate and temper of the <hi>people</hi> with whom your credit and reputation lieth, and whom you fear; <hi>they</hi> are uſually divided in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to three ſorts, two <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treams,</hi> and a <hi>middle</hi> more ſtaid and ſober ſort of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; the two <hi>extrams</hi> are the <hi>profane</hi> and the <hi>giddy, i. e.</hi> ſuch as are <hi>zealous,</hi> but <hi>without knowledge.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. Now let it be ſeriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reckoned what our repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation with theſe two <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treams</hi> is <hi>worrh,</hi> further then it may help us to <hi>ſave</hi> their <hi>ſouls.</hi> Again, How difficult and almoſt
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:160556:105"/> impoſſible it is to have and keep a <hi>good Name,</hi> and a <hi>good Conſcience,</hi> with <hi>either</hi> of theſe: If we be <hi>faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful</hi> to their <hi>ſouls</hi> in reproof of ſin, and preſſing the <hi>power</hi> of godlineſs, will not the <hi>profane</hi> hate us and <hi>ſpeak evil of us?</hi> And let one put it home to you, What conſiderable part of Reputation have you <hi>left</hi> (if you have indeed been thus faithful) with them, to hazard or loſe by your <hi>conformity?</hi> Yea, Whether you are not more certain to contract the <hi>reproach</hi> &amp; revi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing of ſuch perſons by your <hi>Non-conformity?</hi> and whether your <hi>Conformity</hi> may not afford you more <hi>opportunity.</hi> (by being a means of your continuing
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:160556:105"/> in your places) and alſo more <hi>advantage</hi> (bringing your <hi>practice nearer</hi> to their <hi>principles</hi> and deſires) of <hi>winning,</hi> reforming, and ſaving the <hi>ſouls</hi> of the profaner ſort of your peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, then your <hi>Non-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity,</hi> throwing you out of the <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> and far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from the way and <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections</hi> of thoſe people, is likely to do.</p>
               <p n="6">6. As for the <hi>zealous</hi> part, I mean ſuch whoſe <hi>knowledg</hi> is but <hi>ſmall,</hi> and their <hi>zeal much;</hi> I confeſs your <hi>intereſt</hi> in them is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervedly prized, becauſe they <hi>mean well,</hi> and in the main are many of them <hi>truly pious;</hi> yet I judge it very unreaſonable to prize your <hi>intereſt</hi> in their favour
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:160556:106"/> and aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ction above the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of their <hi>ſouls,</hi> the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> and of <hi>God</hi> himſelf; which is to ſet their good <hi>opinion</hi> of us (falſſy taken too) above our <hi>Miniſtry</hi> and the <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Peace,</hi> above our <hi>duty</hi> to God and man. It is poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible we may ſuffer from <hi>good people,</hi> not on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y for <hi>well doing,</hi> but for <hi>doing,</hi> or endeavouring to do them <hi>good;</hi> and a <hi>Peter</hi> through ignorance may act <hi>Satans</hi> part, towards <hi>Chriſt</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; but our <hi>Saviour</hi> hath encouraged us with his own example, to ſacrifice not only our <hi>Names,</hi> but our <hi>Lives,</hi> to <hi>ſave,</hi> if poſſible, the <hi>very perſons</hi> that would take them from us.</p>
               <p n="7">
                  <pb n="187" facs="tcp:160556:106"/> 7. Beſides, when the <hi>Law</hi> for Conformity ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to the <hi>People,</hi> as well as to the <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> perhaps, by their own <hi>neceſſity,</hi> they may learn more modeſty <hi>&amp; charity</hi> towards us.</p>
               <p>And in the mean while theſe cenſures are far more obnoxious to the <hi>cenſure</hi> and reproof of their <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters,</hi> and all ſober peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, for their raſhneſs and uncharitableneſs, then their <hi>Miniſters<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> can ſo much as ſeem to be, by doing their <hi>duty</hi> in a juſt <hi>Conformity:</hi> and, if meerly to <hi>gratifie them,</hi> we ſuſpend obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to our ſuperiors, wee ſeem to ſacrifice <hi>Church,</hi> and <hi>State,</hi> our <hi>ſelves,</hi> and <hi>all,</hi> as far as in us lies, to the very <hi>humours</hi> of our people.</p>
               <p n="8">
                  <pb n="188" facs="tcp:160556:107"/> 8. Our own <hi>experience</hi> (many of us I am ſure) hath ſufficienly <hi>reproached</hi> us already, for our being ſo much <hi>lead</hi> by the <hi>fooliſh fire</hi> of the ſtrange <hi>zeal</hi> of ſuch kind of people; wee have ſeen that there is no <hi>meaſure</hi> in their principles, no <hi>bounds</hi> in their practiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, and many of us have once already, by making them our <hi>guides,</hi> loſt our <hi>way,</hi> our <hi>ſelves,</hi> and our <hi>credits,</hi> and <hi>reputation,</hi> as well with <hi>our ſelves,</hi> as with all <hi>ſober</hi> and well temper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed perſons; and ſhall we now take <hi>ſanctuary there</hi> to <hi>ſave</hi> our <hi>credits,</hi> where our reputation hath <hi>bled,</hi> and our <hi>Names</hi> have ſuffered e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to death already? Is not the good of the
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:160556:107"/> 
                  <hi>Church,</hi> the ſervice of <hi>Souls,</hi> the protection of the <hi>Laws,</hi> and <hi>juſt</hi> obedience to <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>King,</hi> a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>refuge,</hi> and of better <hi>reputation,</hi> then the <hi>opinion</hi> of a few <hi>inconſiderate</hi> cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorious perſons? Let it be wiſely conſidered.</p>
               <p n="9">9. Let us ponder a little the ſentence of <hi>Calvin,</hi> paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed long agon upon ſuch <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Galv.</hi> Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſ. Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bapt. Art. 2.</note> kind of people, the truth of which much late <hi>experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> hath <hi>ſealed</hi> unto; <hi>Cum ſub ſpecie ſtudii perfectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis imperfectionem nullam tolerare poſſumus, aut in corpore, aut in membris Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae, tunc Diabolum nos Tumefacere Superbia, &amp; Hypocriſi ſeducere monea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur;</hi> in which words he plainly <hi>fathers</hi> ſuch blind,
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:160556:108"/> raſh; and cenſorious <hi>zeal</hi> upon the <hi>Devil,</hi> and upon the <hi>works</hi> of the Devil, <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction, Pride,</hi> and <hi>Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">10. Now if we do in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed ſo highly value the <hi>love</hi> of ſuch people, have we not reaſon to anſwer their <hi>Love?</hi> And how can this be better effected then by endeavouring to reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them out of the <hi>ſnare of the Divel,</hi> both by <hi>Doctrine</hi> or good <hi>example;</hi> I mean the rather <hi>for their ſakes,</hi> to yield obedience to <hi>thoſe</hi> things that <hi>our people</hi> ought to know we judge to be <hi>lawful;</hi> and that they may alſo be truly ſatisfied <hi>how ready</hi> we are to do any thing that is not <hi>ſinful,</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then to lay down the
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:160556:108"/> 
                  <hi>Miniſtry</hi> and ſervice of their <hi>Souls;</hi> a far better way, I think, to expreſs our hearty affection to them, then by indulging their <hi>prejudices,</hi> gratify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their <hi>vices,</hi> or out of a ſenſleſs <hi>tenderneſs</hi> of our <hi>intereſt</hi> in them, to ſuffer our ſelves by the power of the <hi>Tempter</hi> to be <hi>ſeduced</hi> with them into a ſtate of <hi>wretched ſeparation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If <hi>all</hi> that hath been ſaid cannot <hi>ſatisfie,</hi> let it alſo be ſeriouſly conſidered, how often our <hi>Saviour</hi> hazard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his <hi>Name</hi> with the <hi>Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> that he might <hi>fulfil</hi> his <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> until he had gotten the <hi>ſlander</hi> of a <hi>friend of Publicans and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners;</hi> that his Apoſtle <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ventured</hi> his <hi>credit</hi> even
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:160556:109"/> with the <hi>Church,</hi> the <hi>pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt</hi> of the Church, that he might anſwer his <hi>call</hi> from heaven, and diſpenſe the <hi>Goſpel</hi> to his <hi>new charge</hi> the <hi>Gentiles:</hi> And laſtly; How doth <hi>Paul</hi> alſo run the ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of a <hi>ſcandalous reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> of <hi>time,</hi> and <hi>compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſerving,</hi> of <hi>men-pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> &amp;c. When to the <hi>Jew</hi> he becomes a <hi>Jew,</hi> and to thoſe <hi>without Law,</hi> as if <hi>without Law;</hi> even <hi>all things</hi> (lawful) to <hi>all men;</hi> which yet he ſticks not at, as himſelf glories, for the <hi>Goſpels ſake,</hi> and that he might obtain opportunity and advantage to <hi>win ſouls.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But beſides theſe <hi>two ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treams,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">11.</note> there's a <hi>midle</hi> ſort of people, that are <hi>ſixed</hi>
                  <pb n="193" facs="tcp:160556:109"/> upon ſober and <hi>ſtaid Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples</hi> of a better reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by far then <hi>either</hi> or <hi>both</hi> of the former; indeed if our <hi>Conformity</hi> ſhould forfeit our <hi>credit</hi> with <hi>theſe;</hi> I ſhould much ſuſpect it.</p>
               <p n="12">12. But here you muſt not underſtand by this <hi>ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber ſort</hi> of people, only the <hi>ſober</hi> people of your <hi>own Pariſhes,</hi> that is too <hi>narrow</hi> and ſhort a <hi>meaſure</hi> of them; but the <hi>ſober</hi> and moderate part of the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> as you may find them in all <hi>ranks</hi> and <hi>qualities, degrees</hi> and <hi>callings</hi> of men, as hath been before more largely obſerved.</p>
               <p n="13">13. Now, I think, I may ſay with <hi>confidence,</hi> that
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:160556:110"/> 
                  <hi>theſe</hi> you will finde either <hi>profeſſedly</hi> for <hi>Conformity</hi> themſelves, or elſe ſo wiſe, ſo juſt, and <hi>charitable</hi> to you, as (unleſs you have <hi>formerly</hi> forfeited your cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit and reputation with <hi>them,</hi> by ſome notorious <hi>appearances</hi> of your <hi>time-ſerving)</hi> to put a <hi>better in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation</hi> upon your humble and peaceable <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to Authority,</hi> then you ſeem to hope for.</p>
               <p>Yea, though your <hi>name</hi> and eſteem ſhould ſeem to <note place="margin">14.</note> be <hi>conſumed</hi> in the <hi>zeal</hi> and <hi>rage</hi> of the <hi>giddy</hi> and <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane</hi> ſort of the people (with whom it cannot <hi>long live)</hi> yet deſpair not, but by your wiſe and ſober <hi>converſations,</hi> your dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence and labours in the
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:160556:110"/> ſervice of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> your peaceable demeanour in <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience</hi> to the <hi>Laws,</hi> there will ariſe, as it were, out of the aſhes of the old, a <hi>New Name,</hi> and better re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation to you, in the <hi>good opinion</hi> of this better generation, the wiſe and <hi>ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber ſort</hi> of the people.</p>
               <p>15. However caſt the worſt; thou haſt thus <hi>ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficed</hi> thy <hi>Name</hi> for the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of thy <hi>duty</hi> to <hi>God</hi> and the King, to the <hi>Church</hi> and thy <hi>Charge,</hi> &amp; no doubt to thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e own <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> if this be all thy <hi>ſcruple;</hi> for I cannot be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that <hi>he</hi> that ſo much values the good <hi>opinion</hi> of the <hi>vulgar,</hi> can ever have a <hi>good opinion</hi> of <hi>himſelf;</hi> or <hi>he</hi> that dare hazard the
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:160556:111"/> 
                  <hi>peace</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> for his <hi>credit</hi> with the <hi>people,</hi> can have much quiet in his own <hi>breaſt;</hi> or <hi>one</hi> that hath more <hi>confidence</hi> in the <hi>eſteem</hi> of the <hi>multi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ude</hi> than in the <hi>favour</hi> of his <hi>Prince,</hi> or the <hi>protection</hi> of the <hi>Laws,</hi> can eaſily <hi>ſatisfie</hi> his own <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For I muſt needs confeſs <note place="margin">16.</note> with that famous <hi>Church, Civilibus legibus, quae cum</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Confeſ. Suev. <hi>c.</hi> 14.</note> 
                  <hi>pietate non pugnant eo quiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que Chriſtianus paret prom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptius, quo fide Chriſti eſt imbutus plenius;</hi> That eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Chriſtian, by how much the more he ſavours of the <hi>faith</hi> of Chriſt, by ſo much the more prompt and ready he is to conform to the <hi>Laws</hi> of <hi>men,</hi> which are not contrary to the Laws of <hi>God.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:160556:111"/>
            <head>The Table.</head>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>I. WHAT are things <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different?</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>page</hi> 1.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>II. Whether is any thing Indifferent in the exerciſe of <hi>Religion?</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>p.</hi> 3.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>III. Whether may things Indifferent be <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed?</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>8.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>IV. Whether may they conduce to <hi>order</hi> in Gods worſhip?</cell>
                     <cell>13.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>V. What are thoſe things Indifferent that <hi>may be</hi> impoſed?</cell>
                     <cell>16.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb facs="tcp:160556:112"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>VI. Whether may things Indifferent be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed <hi>quatenus ſuch?</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>pag.</hi> 25</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>VII. What doth ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der things indifferent <hi>fit</hi> to be impoſed?</cell>
                     <cell>30</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>VIII. What are thoſe <hi>General Rules</hi> of <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture</hi> that <hi>limit</hi> the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of things indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent?</cell>
                     <cell>32</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>IX. How are <hi>private</hi> perſons to demean them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves under <hi>ſuch</hi> impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions of things indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent in the worſhip of <hi>God?</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>51</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>X. What are we do, when things <hi>in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves neceſſary</hi> are <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired</hi> by Authority?</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>pag.</hi> 55</cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb facs="tcp:160556:112"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>XI. What are we to do, when things <hi>expedient</hi> are required?</cell>
                     <cell>61</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>XII. What, when things <hi>purely Indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent?</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>65</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>XIII. What, when things <hi>inexpedient?</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>72</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Where it is enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1. Whether a thing that we <hi>judge inexpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient</hi> may be done <hi>in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience</hi> to Authority?</cell>
                     <cell>81</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2. VVhether it may not be <hi>expedient,</hi> aſwell as <hi>lawfull,</hi> ſometimes to obey in things <hi>lawfull</hi> but <hi>inexpedient?</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>p. 85</cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb facs="tcp:160556:113"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>3. VVhether the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of <hi>Peace, Duty,</hi> and <hi>Safety,</hi> may not render <hi>ſuch</hi> Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence both <hi>lawfull</hi> and <hi>expedient?</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>91, 99, 104</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>XIV. VVhat are we to do, when things <hi>ſinfull</hi> are impoſed?</cell>
                     <cell>116</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>VVhere enquire,</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>I. VVhen things <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terially</hi> and really ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full?</cell>
                     <cell>119</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>II. VVhat are we to do, when things are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired which <hi>we judge ſinfull?</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>pag.</hi> 121</cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb facs="tcp:160556:113"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>VVhere enquire,</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>I. VVherein the <hi>rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity</hi> and <hi>appearance</hi> of <hi>Superſtition</hi> conſiſts?</cell>
                     <cell>129</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>II. VVhether things <hi>formerly</hi> uſed with <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition,</hi> are to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted <hi>ſuperſtitious ſtill?</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>137</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>III. VVhether the <hi>ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificancy</hi> of things im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed render them <hi>ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious?</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>144</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>IV. VVhether to obey the <hi>Laws of men</hi> in things <hi>Indifferent,</hi> be to betray our <hi>Chriſtian Liberty?</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>pag.</hi> 151</cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb facs="tcp:160556:114"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>III. VVhat we are to do, when <hi>we</hi> conceive the thing required to be <hi>lawfull,</hi> but <hi>others judg</hi> it to be <hi>ſinfull,</hi> and will be <hi>offended</hi> at our obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience?</cell>
                     <cell>160</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2. Whether a <hi>humane Law</hi> can take off the Force of the <hi>Scripture-Rule, not to uſe our Liberty to the offence of the weak?</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>174</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:160556:114"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
